<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A looking-glasse for papists to see their owne deformities in matters of faith, and religion: and for formall protestants; to make them more carefull of the true profession of Iesus Christ: lest at any time they fall away from the sinceritie of the Gospell of Christ. With a briefe history of the Popes liues, from the first three hundred yeeres after Christ, vntill Paul the fift.</title>
            <author>R. W., minister in Norfolk.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14601</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854518</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19944</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14601)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19944)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1562:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A looking-glasse for papists to see their owne deformities in matters of faith, and religion: and for formall protestants; to make them more carefull of the true profession of Iesus Christ: lest at any time they fall away from the sinceritie of the Gospell of Christ. With a briefe history of the Popes liues, from the first three hundred yeeres after Christ, vntill Paul the fift.</title>
                  <author>R. W., minister in Norfolk.</author>
                  <author>Woods, Richard, minister of Frettenham, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Wrathall, Richard, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Burges, John, 1561?-1635.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathaniel Newbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Foreword signed: R.W. a poore minister in Norffolke; ætatis suæ. 74.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Richard Woods and to Richard Wrathall.</note>
                  <note>Edited by John Burges, whose name appears on [A]3v.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19944:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19944:1"/>
            <p>A LOOKING-GLASSE FOR PAPISTS: To ſee their owne Deformities in matters of Faith, and Religion: And for formall Protestants; to make them more carefull of the true profeſsion of IESVS CHRIST: leſt at any time they fall away from the ſinceritie of the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>With a briefe Hiſtory of the Popes liues, from the firſt three hundred yeeres after Christ, vntill <hi>Paul</hi> the fift.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Of Babylon, There came a voyce from heauen, ſaying: Come away from her, my people, that ye be not partakers of her ſinnes; lest ye be partakers of her plagues.</p>
               <bibl>Reu. 18. 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the destruction of Babylon (Revelation 18.4)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19944:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19944:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS COVNTRIMEN, the Papiſts in ENGLAND, R. W. wiſheth all encreaſe of knowledge in Spirituall things, with a deſire to know the Truth, and power of CHRIST crucified.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>RETHREN,</hi> my hearts deſire (with <hi>Paul)</hi> and earnest prayer to God for you, is, that you might be ſaued. For of many of you I may ſay, <hi>You haue a zeale, but not according to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge:</hi> whom I chiefly pitty. But I can not ſo ſay of many: who <hi>with-hold the truth in vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> their conſciences daily accuſing them, that they ſtriue against the light, which ſhineth in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; namely, the word of God: <hi>which is a Lanterne vnto our feete, and a light vnto our paths,</hi> to direct vs in all doubts and difficulties in matters of ſaluation: The want of the knowledge whereof, is the maine cauſe of all er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, as ſayth our Sauiour Christ, <hi>Math. 22. 29. Ye erre, not knowing the Scriptures, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>Iohn 5. 39. Search the Scriptures, for in them yee haue eternall life:
<pb facs="tcp:19944:3"/> and they are they that teſtifie of me.</hi> But indeede the god of this world, euen the Diuell, and Sathanas (who knoweth that his kingdome is aſſaulted by them, and finally ſhall be ouerthrowne by this breath of his mouth) laboureth by all poſsible meanes, to ſtoppe the courſe thereof. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath ſet his Agent, the <hi>Pope,</hi> on worke, to take from you the knowledge thereof, to the end, to keepe you in the darkeneſſe of Idolatrie and ſuperſtition; that ſo his king dome may be continued, and increaſed, amongſt the chilaren of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe. Elſe why hath hee cauſed the Scriptures in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue to be publiquely burnt? and the owners of ſuch Bookes, held, and condemned for heretickes, and their bodies alſo conſumed with fire? Againe, why doth hee deliuer the ſmall portions, or fragments of Scripture (which hee vſeth in his Lyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rgie vnto the people) in an vnknowne tongue: Teaching them alſo to pray in Latine, which they vnderſtand not; whereas the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Cor. 14. 19.</hi> ſayth: <hi>I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Congregation, ſpeake fiue words to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then tenne thouſand words in a ſtrange tongue:</hi> verſe 11. and <hi>16. how ſhall they that occupy the roome of the vnlearned ſay,</hi> Amen, <hi>at the giuing of thankes?</hi> And againe, verſe <hi>23. If one come in vnlearned, will he not ſay, yee are out of your wittes? &amp;c.</hi> See the whole Chapter: Notwithſtanding the Pope, as the Diuels instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hath taken from you the vſe of your owne language in Gods ſeruice (pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ended) the fountaine of liuing water, I mean the Scriptures, and <hi>haue digged pits that will holde no water;</hi> I meane their owne decrees, traditions, and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: which they put vpon the people instead of the word of God, as a rule of life to be obſerued, and kept, vpon paine of the Popes curſe. Beloued Countreymen, conſider I beſeech you, what I ſay, and ſuffer not the Diuell, by him, to keepe
<pb facs="tcp:19944:3"/> your ſoules captiue, and refuſe not the voyce of the <hi>wiſe Charmers, Pſalme 58. 5.</hi> Come, and heare our Miniſterie, our prayers, and preaching: and ſuſpect betimes (as others haue done of late, as zealous in your profeſsion as your ſelues) that all is not well on your ſide: while they keepe from you the knowledge of your owne euidence, I meane the Scriptures, which propoundeth vnto you your right in that immortall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance in heauen; purchaſed vnto you onely by his moſt precious bloud-ſhedding: and by faith in him alone obtained. The Lord giue you a right vnderstanding in all things. And accept, I pray you, of my poore Labours, which is but the glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after other mens harueſts. Let not preiudice, or olde er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, cauſe you to refuſe the gift of a friend, that meaneth well vnto you. It will eaſe you of the ſearch of many Authors, and moſt of them Papiſts, for religion, as your ſelues, &amp;c. You dwell not in <hi>Rome,</hi> nor vnder the Popes command (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the fault be in your ſelues;) where indeed it would be the danger of your liues to haue any Engliſh Booke of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or other bookes againſt the Pope, or any point of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: But in a kingdome (which thorow Gods mercy) hath ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the Pope and Poperie many dayes ſince. Vſe therefore your libertie: and ſee what they whom you hold for enemies, can ſay againſt your errours. If you refuſe this aduice, it is not the Pope that can ſtand you in ſtead in the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>but your condemnation ſhal be ſo much the more iuſt, becauſe you haue refuſed counſell, Ezech. 2. 5.</hi> The Lord giue you a heart to conſider of theſe things aright.</p>
            <p>Your well-willer in Christ Ieſus, <hi>R. W.</hi> a poore Miniſter in Norffolke; <hi>Aetatis ſuae. 74.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19944:4"/>
            <head>¶ The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader; by how much the ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time of the Diuells rage againſt Gods Church is to indure, by ſo much the more fiercely doth hee incite his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to beſtirre themſelues for to perſecute the people of God; yea, if it were poſſible, to deſtroy them for euer: which, although it be reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Almighty God, who doth ſo gouerne and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect his Children, that <hi>the Gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt them;</hi> inſomuch, that all true Louers of Truth and Godlineſſe, may reioyce and be comforted in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance thereof: yet may wee not ſo ſlumber in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, as to neglect the meanes of our ſafety, and of the impugning of the powers of Sathan, eſpecially the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Anti-chriſt; but euery one muſt indeuour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to doe that which belongs vnto him.</p>
            <p>To this end, not long ſince (according to the truſt repoſed in me by that Reuerend &amp; worthy man, maſter Doctor <hi>Burges</hi>) I aduentured vpon thy courteous ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation, with one Treatiſe, called, <hi>The Popes deadly Wound,</hi> which, hauing already found ſome kinde en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement at thy hands, I could not keepe backe this ſecond, committed vnto my diſpoſe by the ſame Learned man, a little before his Trauailes into forraine Countries, that ſo, as with two Stones out of one Siing,
<pb facs="tcp:19944:4"/> the great blaſpheming Giant may the more eaſily be layd groueling. It is the worke of a very auncient and graue Miniſter of GODS Word; and very briefe and pithie. I hope thy acceptation of my good-will: and I beſeech GOD for CHRISTS ſake, to make it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable vnto thee.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19944:5"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 THAT <hi>Peter</hi> had no Supremacy ouer the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. fol. 1.</item>
               <item>2 That <hi>Peter</hi> neuer ſate Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> 7</item>
               <item>3 An Examination how the Popes ſucceede <hi>Peter.</hi> 10</item>
               <item>4 The time when the Pope beganne: with the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of their liues, in briefe, from the firſt three hundred yeeres after Chriſt, vntil Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fift, &amp;c. 11. 12. 13. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>5 A briefe Recapitulation of their liues, the better to finde out the Hiſtories.</item>
               <item>6 The Concluſion for Doctrine, with the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 79</item>
               <item>7 Arguments to proue the Pope Anti-chriſt. 101</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19944:5"/>
            <head>A LOOKING-GLASSE FOR PAPISTS.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>1. Againſt <hi>Peters</hi> Supremacy.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>MARKE 10. 42.</bibl>
                     <p>The Lords of the Nations haue domination ouer them, &amp;c. But it ſhall not be ſo among you: but whoſoeuer will be great among you, let him be your ſeruant; and whoſoeuer will be chiefe, ſhall be ſeruant of all: for euen the Sonne of man came not to be ſerued, but to ſerue, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Luke 22. 26.</bibl>
                     <p>Let the greateſt among you be as the leaſt, and the chiefeſt as he that ſerueth.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Matthew 20. 26.</bibl>
                     <p>Whoſoeuer will be great among you, let him be your ſeruant; and whoſoeuer will be chiefe, let him be your ſeruant, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19944:6"/>
               <p>The Papiſts places for Supremacy.
<label>1 COR. 12. 22.</label> 
                  <hi>The head cannot ſay to the feete, I haue no neede of you.</hi> Say they: This muſt be the Paſtor ouer the Flocke: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Of <hi>Peter</hi> in reſpect of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle ſpeaketh of no head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, but conſidering the conſent of the members one for another, hee intendeth that ſo it ſhould be in the Church for auoiding of contention; not as the Popes, that diſgrace, ſubiect, yea, killeth Kings, the chiefe members of the Church, and many other great Diuines, as <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Prage,</hi> worthy men; onely becauſe they would not aſſent with them.</p>
               <p>Matth. 16. 18. <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and vpon this</hi> Peter, <hi>will I build my Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> With ſhame enough, for the vulgar, which vpon paine of the Popes curſe no man muſt al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, hath <hi>Super hanc petram;</hi> that is, vpon this Rocke: which was <hi>Peters</hi> confeſſion Chriſt meant, euen himſelfe the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Church; as a Rocke. Hereunto <hi>Tunſtall</hi> and <hi>Stokeley,</hi> two Popiſh Biſhops agree. 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 11. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foundation can no man lay, then that which is laide, which is, Ieſus Chriſt, the chiefe Shepheard.</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 2. 4. <hi>Where the chiefe Shepheard ſhall appeare, &amp;c.</hi> Not the Pope I trowe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matthew 16. 19. To thee will I giue the Keyes, &amp;c.</hi> By
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19944:6"/> this they vnderſtand the fulneſſe of power Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, to make him head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> The queſtion being propounded to them all, <hi>Peter</hi> anſwering, one for all; therefore together one for them all receiued this power: and therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer Chriſt promiſed to <hi>Peter,</hi> he promiſed to him, to them alike; as <hi>Matt.</hi> 18. 18. and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. 23. it is ſaid, not to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, but to them all: <hi>Whatſoeuer ye bind on earth, ſhall be, &amp;c. And whoſoeuer ſinnes ye remit, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſostome</hi> on this place ſaith; <hi>What therefore did</hi> Peter, <hi>the mouth of all the Apoſtles, and crowne of the whole Company?</hi> When all were asked the queſtion, hee alone anſwered, and being asked of the opinion of the common people, they all anſwered: but when hee asked them of their owne opinion, <hi>Peter</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtart forth, and preuenting the reſt, ſaid; <hi>Thou art Chriſt that Sonne of God:</hi> Againe, <hi>Vpon this Rocke;</hi> that is, that Faith, and Confeſſion: And againe, <hi>The Keyes of the Kingdome of Heauen, &amp;c.</hi> the ſame is common to them all, <hi>Iohn 20. 21. 22. 23. Peter</hi> after diſſwaded Chriſt to die, whereupon <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſaith: <hi>From hence ſurely we plainely ſee, that he ſpake not before of himſelfe. Keyes.</hi> This is a Metaphor, intending the publike Office of the Apoſtles, the publike preaching of the Goſpell through the World, which yet they were not to enter vpon, till they were fully furniſhed. <hi>Luk. 24 47. Acts</hi> 1. 4. Theſe Keyes are not deliuered to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, for hee ſaith in the future tence; <hi>I will giue;</hi> not doe, or haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. <hi>Luk</hi> 24. 49. Where the commiſſion is giuen to them all, not naming <hi>Peter. Mat. 28. 19. Mar. 16. 15. Ioh. 20. 21. Goe into all the World, preach the Goſpell to euery creature.</hi> But the full power was not vntill the fiftieth day after
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19944:7"/> the reſurrection, when the holy Ghoſt came vpon euery one of them; and now they executed their Office in preaching the Goſpell, which was, the Keyes to open the Kingdome of Heauen. If <hi>Peter</hi> onely had the Keyes to open the kingdome of heauen, what ſhould haue become of the greateſt part of the World: yea, of vs Gentiles?</p>
               <p>Their fourth place, <hi>Luke 22. 31. Simon, Simon, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than hath deſired to ſift you, &amp;c.</hi> If to ſtrengthen the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; then he muſt be ſupreame head.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> Whereas the Papiſts vnderſtand by <hi>you,</hi> the other Apoſtles, that were to accuſe Chriſt, that chooſing twelue men to worke, being Maſter to all, (and giuing graces alike to all) would ſend them to a fellow laborer, to be taught after his departure: but <hi>Peter</hi> ſhall giue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in this point, that he meant not ſo; but by <hi>brethren</hi> he meaneth all the faithfull. 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 10. Wherefore bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren giue alwayes diligence to make your calling and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the reſt of the Apoſtles call the faithfull, <hi>brethren,</hi> as children of one Father, 2 <hi>Theſſ. 2. 1. We beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, &amp;c.</hi> and 3. 1. <hi>Furthermore, Brethren pray for vs:</hi> and verſe 6. <hi>Rom. 12. 1. I beſeech you brethren by the mercy of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. 1 Pet.</hi> 5. 8. 9. So that by Brethren, our Sauiour meant the faithfull, whom <hi>Peter,</hi> and the reſt ſhould ſtrengthen. To this end, <hi>verſe</hi> 2. he exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to <hi>feede the Flocke,</hi> and to take care of them. And <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 14. 22. Strengthened them.</p>
               <p>Their fift place, <hi>Iohn 21. 15. 17. Feede my Sheepe.</hi> This they vnderſtand of <hi>Peter</hi> to the reſt of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> This was a Commandement giuen before of Chriſt in his former Commiſſion, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. 21. Giuen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19944:7"/> to <hi>Peter</hi> with all the Apoſtles: <hi>As my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you. Receiue the holy Ghoſt. Whoſoeuer ſinnes ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore this was no new charge: but willeth him to looke to that, leſt he might ſtart aſide, as he had done before; <hi>Matthew 16. 22. Goe after me Sathan.</hi> And <hi>Matthew</hi> 26. He denyed him three times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feede my Lambes. Sheepe:</hi> This is a Metaphor taken from a Flocke of Sheepe, and Lambes. Now Chriſt is the good Shepheard, that hath <hi>giuen his life for the Sheepe; Iohn</hi> 10. 11. and 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1. 4. The Sheepe-fold is the Church, and the Sheepe and Lambes, are the faithfull, to be gathered into the Sheepe-fold; <hi>Iohn 10. 1. 16. By his Subſtitutes, Apoſtles, Paſtors, &amp;c. Ephe.</hi> 4. 11. The Church is called, <hi>a Flocke. Luke 12. 32. Feare not little Flocke.</hi> Acts 20. 28. <hi>Take heede vnto all the Flocke. Paul</hi> ſpeaking to the Paſtors, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 5. ſpeaking to the Elders. <hi>Feede the Flocke of Chriſt, which dependeth vpon you.</hi> Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> had no authority ouer the other Apoſtles, but they and he had one commandement and commiſſion to goe into the whole World, to preach the Goſpell, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine Miniſters.</p>
               <p>The ſixt place, <hi>Acts 1. 15. Peter</hi> propoundeth an ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be made of a new Apoſtle; <hi>Ergo</hi> head of the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> This proueth that he was the Prolocutor, or common-ſpeaker, as with vs in Parliament, and might be the firſt in place, for Order, but not the Elector; for that was done by them all: as <hi>Acts 1. 22. And they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed two, not</hi> Peter <hi>alone, and the election was of God di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſing the Lots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſeauenth place, <hi>Acts 15. 7. He is preſident of the Counſell of the Apoſtles.</hi> He ſpeaketh firſt, he concludeth, with lie and all.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19944:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> The Text ſhall confute this. He, as is ſaid, was firſt in order, (but not in authority) as the common ſpeaker: <hi>verſe 12. Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake with great ſilence of the reſt, and when they ceaſed, <hi>verſe 13. Iames</hi> anſwered; Whoſe ſentence preuailed: And then not <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but all the Apoſtles and Elders, and the whole Church concluded. So Peters primacy of order, was not the Popes ſupremacy.</p>
               <p>The eight place, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 18. Paul <hi>after three yeeres came to ſee</hi> Peter, (ſay they) <hi>to doe him honor: Ergo</hi> Superior.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> If it were ſo that he came to honour <hi>Peter,</hi> this proues not his primacy; for then ſhould Wiues be ſuperiors to their Husbands: For, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 7. ſaith; <hi>Let Wiues be ſubiect to their Husbands:</hi> yet he ſaith, <hi>They muſt giue them honour. Ahaſhureoſh</hi> honoured <hi>Mor decai,</hi> yet he was not aboue him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome, 1 Gal.</hi> ſaith; <hi>That</hi> Paul <hi>was</hi> Peters <hi>Peere in dignity. Ambroſe</hi> there ſaith, Paul <hi>was euen ſuch another as</hi> Peter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> there ſaith; <hi>Their authority to be equall, and for</hi> Pauls <hi>honour, what hee wanted in time, is ſupplyed by Chriſts glory;</hi> not as the reſt, made an Apoſtle on the earth, but from heauen, while he now raigned in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gal. 11. Paul</hi> himſelfe ſaith; <hi>He was an Apoſtle, not of men, nor by men, but by Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> Againe, 2. 6. Of them which ſeemed to be chiefe, <hi>I was not taught:</hi> And verſe 11. he ſaith; <hi>When</hi> Peter <hi>came to Antioch, I with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood him to his face: for he was worthy to be blamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ninth place, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 18. as before. <hi>That he tarryed with him</hi> fifteene <hi>dayes: no ſmall honour,</hi> ſay they.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19944:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere. Mary,</hi> the chiefe of women, went a great iourney to ſalute <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and taryed with her three moneths, no ſmall time; the Babe ſprang in her wombe at her ſalutation, yea, ſhee was filled with the holy Ghoſt: You will not ſay, I trow, <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was aboue <hi>Mary.</hi> Therefore <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Chryſoſt. Theodoret, Ierome,</hi> and others ſay, that <hi>Paul</hi> came to <hi>Peter,</hi> not to learne of him, but of reuerence and loue to be acquainted with him: <hi>Ergo Paul</hi> acknowledged no ſupremacy.</p>
               <p>The tenth place, <hi>Iohn 10. 16. There ſhall be one Flocke, and one Shepheard:</hi> which is, the Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwere.</hi> The Text plainely ſheweth it to be Chriſt, who by the preaching of the Goſpell gathereth them that are not yet called, and ſo to the end of the World; that ſo there may be <hi>one Sheepe-fold, Iohn</hi> 10. 16. Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe being the <hi>chiefe Shepheard, 1 Pet.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
               <p>In all theſe places we can finde no ſupremacy in <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> yet the Pope will needes be his ſucceſſour. Now let vs ſee how he ſucceedes; and becauſe he ſtandeth much on the place, though many wretches ſucceede good men in place, yet we will examine it: but if he be <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour, he muſt ſucceed him rather in labour, in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell of Chriſt, and in holy life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Firſt of the place, whether <hi>Peter</hi> ſate euer Biſhop of Rome.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter</hi> was an Apoſtle. Now the Apoſtles were not deputed to any certaine place; but had the whole World for their Dioceſſe.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19944:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marke 16. 15. Goe into all the World, preach the Goſpell to euery creature, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. Therefore <hi>Peter</hi> writeth vnto the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which he had planted in <hi>Pontus, Galatia, Capadocia, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Bethinia,</hi> making no mention of <hi>Italie,</hi> or <hi>Rome;</hi> though I denie not, but he might be there as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but not to reſide there: for that had beene to goe beyond his Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>The Papiſts alledge for their proofe, <hi>Hierome de viris illuſtribus:</hi> That <hi>Peter</hi> ſate Biſhop at <hi>Antioch</hi> 7. yeeres, and then went to <hi>Rome</hi> the ſecond of <hi>Claudius,</hi> where he ſate 25. yeeres, euen to the 14. yeere of <hi>Nero,</hi> at what time he dyed.</p>
               <p>Now let vs examine this point. <hi>Paul</hi> was conuerted the firſt yeere after Chriſt, and tarryed in <hi>Arabia</hi> three yeeres: <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 17. 18. Then he went to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit <hi>Peter,</hi> the fourth yeere after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the 22. of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius.</hi> Then <hi>Peter</hi> was one at <hi>Ieruſalem, Acts</hi> 12. 3. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Peter</hi> was put in priſon the ſecond, or third of <hi>Claudius, Anno Chriſti</hi> 11. and <hi>Acts 13. 14, Paul</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Antioch</hi> the eight of <hi>Claudius;</hi> where it is not like that <hi>Peter</hi> was: for then there had beene little neede of him. Againe, <hi>Luke</hi> would haue made ſome mention of him: for <hi>Paul</hi> came twice to <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 14. 21. 26. and there they aboad long time with the Diſciples; no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Peters</hi> being there. About this time <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> goe vp to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to conferre with the Apoſtles about Circumciſion; where the Apoſtles called a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell about that matter: where <hi>Peter</hi> was the firſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but <hi>Iames</hi> concludeth the point; and this was the eleuenth yere of <hi>Claudius:</hi> And they wrote Letters vnto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19944:9"/> to the Brethren that were at <hi>Antiochia:</hi> So wee ſee that <hi>Peter</hi> was not yet there, but at <hi>Ieruſalem, Anno Chriſti 18. Claudij</hi> 10. That he might be at <hi>Antioch</hi> as an Apoſtle, we denie not, but when he went, or how long he tarried, the Scripture ſheweth not, neither can Papiſts proue.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Peter</hi> being at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the tenth of <hi>Claudius,</hi> and <hi>Claudius</hi> dyed foure yeeres after. Now <hi>Nero</hi> ſucceeding, raigned but 14. yeeres; foure and 14. make but eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene: How could <hi>Peter</hi> ſit ſeauen yeeres Biſhop of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> and after 25. yeeres at <hi>Rome;</hi> which maketh 32. yeeres? So they muſt put 4. or fiue Emperors raignes to make vp the number, that is, the firſt of <hi>Domitian:</hi> for <hi>Galba</hi> raigned but ſeauen moneths, <hi>Otho</hi> but three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> nine yeeres, <hi>Titus</hi> two yeeres, <hi>Domitian</hi> fifteene yeeres: out of which if you take two yeeres, makes it vp the 32. and <hi>Peter</hi> was dead 14. yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, by their owne confeſſion, the laſt of <hi>Nero:</hi> and then we finde another in the place, one <hi>Anaclet.</hi> To conclude, they can neuer proue he ſate Biſhop at <hi>Antioch</hi> ſeauen yeeres, nor at <hi>Rome</hi> at all.</p>
               <p>Here a Friar of their owne, one <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> skilfull in Antiquities, and the Popes Secretary. <hi>It is cleere</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and manifeſtly knowne by the</hi> Acts <hi>of the Apostles, and</hi> Pauls <hi>Epiſtle to the</hi> Galathians, <hi>that for nine yeeres ſpace af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts death, vntill the ſecond of</hi> Claudius, Peter <hi>neuer went out of Iury:</hi> Wherefore, if he came to <hi>Rome</hi> at that time, it followeth of neceſſity, that he did not ſit ſeauen yeeres at <hi>Antioch</hi> before he came thither. For from the ſecond of <hi>Claudius,</hi> vntill his death, is about 25. yeeres: and though the ancient Writers ſay, He ſate at <hi>Rome,</hi> yet it followeth not, that he aboade ſtill in the City: For in the fourth yeere after his comming thither, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19944:10"/> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and was preſent at the Counſell there: Thence he came to <hi>Antioch,</hi> and there continued ſeauen yeeres, vntill the raigne of <hi>Nero,</hi> when he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> where hee repaired the Roman Church, which was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying. After that, when he had trauelled almoſt tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row all <hi>Europe,</hi> he returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> in the firſt of <hi>Nero,</hi> and there was put to death. Thus far <hi>Onuphrius.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is but a tale, that he ſate Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> 25. yeeres, or at all; but that hee was there as an Apoſtle, as hath beene ſaid before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Now come wee to examine how the Pope ſucceedeth Peter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PEter,</hi> if he were at <hi>Rome,</hi> it was, as he was an Apoſtle, to preach the Goſpell, and to eſtabliſh the Church there, as he did in other places, euen as <hi>Paul</hi> did, and the reſt of the Apoſtles through the World; according to their commiſſion and commandement giuen by Chriſt; <hi>Matthew</hi> 28. 19. Againe, he was there to confirme with his bloud the Doctrine taught, and was obedient to the Emperour, and ſuffered death at his command: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he left an enſample for doctrine, and manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to his ſucceſſors.</p>
               <p>Now let vs ſee how the Pope ſucceedeth <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He teacheth not Chriſt the onely meanes of ſaluation, but his own traditions, merits, worſhipping of Saints, &amp;c. and perſecuteth, and putteth them to death, that obey not his decrees, and commands. Secondly, he yeeldeth not obedience to authority, as <hi>Peter</hi> taught, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. 1 <hi>Peter 2. 13. Submit your ſelues vnto all manner
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19944:10"/> or dinances of men, for the Lords ſake, whether vnto the King, as the Superior, or to Rulers ſent by him for puniſhment, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Paul, Rom. 13. Let euery ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers, &amp;c.</hi> Whoſoeuer reſiſteth power, reſiſteth Gods ordinance.</p>
               <p>But the Pope commandeth Kings, curſeth them, and killeth them; to that end he hath his triple Crowne, and elaymeth ſoueraignty ouer the Church, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the treaſure of the World: whereas <hi>Peter</hi> had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gold, nor ſiluer, <hi>Acts</hi> 3. 6. The Lot of the Church is to be perſecuted, not to perſecute: we muſt not looke to fare better then our Maſter, ſaith <hi>Chriſt; Iohn</hi> 15. 20. Remember the words: <hi>I ſaid vnto you, the ſeruant is not greater then the Maſter; if they haue perſecuted me, they will alſo perſecute you.</hi> If the Pope be Chriſts ſeruant, as hee calles himſelfe, <hi>Seruant of Seruants;</hi> let him ſhew his markes for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> as <hi>Paul, Gal. 6. 17. Behold, I beare in my body the markes of the Lord Ieſus.</hi> See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. And therefore we conclude, the Pope to be Antichriſt, not Chriſts ſeruant, nor <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Now enquire we the time when it is like the <hi>Pope</hi> beganne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REuelation</hi> 20. 2. We haue a manifeſt Prophecie, that Sathan ſhould be bound, which ranged at pleaſure in the vnchriſtian World, that is, before Chriſt; who ſhall lighten things that are hid in darkeneſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 5. and <hi>Luk. 1. 79. &amp; Ioh. 1. 5. &amp; Ioh. 3. 19. This is condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that light is come into the World, and men loued darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. Act.</hi> 17. 30. The time of this ignorance God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19944:11"/> not, but now biddeth all men, <hi>Euery, &amp;c.</hi> Now this light is Chriſt, and the preaching of the Goſpell. Sathan therefore muſt be bound one thouſand yeeres from Chriſts preaching, that he ſhould not through the darkeneſſe of error, vexe men as he had done, though their bodies be not freed from the Croſſe, and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may be like their Maſter. Now the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> with other Biſhops, <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Antioch, Conſtantinople,</hi> and the reſt that ſucceeded, not at <hi>Rome,</hi> but whereſoeuer; for preaching Chriſt cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, were ſo occupied, what with preaching, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Croſſe, for the ſpace of the firſt 300. yeeres, as they had no leyſure to dreame of Supremacy: After which time (as Reſt breeds Ruſt) ſo by little and little they grew ambitious, and now and then one Biſhop or other, would affect priority: ſo as about the end of the next 300. yeeres, they began to deſire primacy, but not ſupremacy: As <hi>Policarpe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> challenged the firſt place, 426. yeeres after Chriſt. <hi>Gelacius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> after him about 445. <hi>Iustine</hi> Emperor of <hi>Rome,</hi> made <hi>Miſda</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> Patriarch, about 520. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſame time, <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> Biſhop, was called vniuerſall Biſhop. <hi>Iohn</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> a good man, was put in priſon, and dyed for the truth. <hi>Pelagius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was the firſt that challenged the primacy by Scripture. <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> called himſelfe vniuerſall Biſhop, 582. <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> firſt of that name, reproued <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> for calling himſelfe vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, 591. Before him <hi>Iohn</hi> the third, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> decreed that none ſhould be called <hi>ſummus Sacerdos,</hi> or vniuerſal Biſhop, about 566. All this while no thought
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19944:11"/> of a Pope, or of <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor in <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>Phocas,</hi> ſeruant to <hi>Mauricius</hi> Emperor, killed his Maſter, the Empreſſe, and children moſt cruelly: At this time <hi>Boniface</hi> the third Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> obtained of this Butcher the title to be called vniuerſall. Biſhop, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 607.</p>
               <p>Note that the primacy of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> was eſtabliſhed by a murtherer, and a Traytor, who dyed miſerably: for the 612. of Chriſt, he was ſlaine by the Souldiers of his Guard. <hi>Abbas Veſper,</hi> &amp; others ſay, that <hi>Heraclius</hi> and <hi>Perſius</hi> ſlew him, cutting off his hands and feete: others adde, that his priuy members were cut off, and his body burnt. <hi>Eſtate Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the 3. liued but 9. moneths (ſo ſoone his pride came to an end) whoſe life and decrees periſhed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Anno</hi> 607.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin</hi> the 1. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was buffeted by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour for reprouing him, being an heretike, and was further vilely entreated, baniſhed from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> (whither the Emperour ſent for him) to <hi>Pontus,</hi> with his tongue cut out, 649. Yet <hi>Rome</hi> no Supremacy, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Emperour, both in creation, and depoſing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtance</hi> Emperour, ſpoyled <hi>Rome</hi> (becauſe the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops were not willing he ſhould remoue thither) more in ſeuen dayes, then all the Barbarians did in 360. yeers. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 662.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vitelian,</hi> called Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to him the Emperour by ſingular grace confirmed the priuiledges of the Church, which notwithſtanding, hee after brake, and made them of no force, <hi>Faſci. Temporum.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:19944:12"/>
               <p>The ſixt Counſel of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> approued Maſſe in the Latine tongue. The Greeke Prieſts were permitted to liue in mariage, but not the Prieſts of the Weſt-Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: None to anſwere for a Childe, but ſuch as knew the Lords Prayer, and the Beliefe of the faithfull. In the ſecond Volume of Counſels, none to vow not to marry, and that Prieſts which ſeparated themſelues from their Wiues, becauſe of their ſacred Orders, ſhould be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Communion. <hi>Peter viret in dialogo,</hi> to them of <hi>Orbe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 12. &amp; 13. Counſell of <hi>Tolledo,</hi> ſuch were Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamiſed, as forbid eating of fleſh. <hi>Pet. Viret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the 2. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> obtained of the Emperor, that the election of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> made by the people, Clergie, and Souldiers, without attending any more the authority of the Emperour, ſhould be lawfull. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 685.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> the 1. was choſen in a Schiſme: he was in danger for condemning the Hereſie of the Monotholites: He ſent <hi>Vmbred</hi> to the Friſons to conuert them to the faith, 688.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philippicus Bardanius,</hi> Emperour, made an Edict that all the Images of Saints ſhould be taken from Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. 717. and that by conſent of <hi>Iohn,</hi> Patriarke of <hi>Constantinople.</hi> No maruell though Pope, and Papiſts be of another minde; for they haue left the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement out of the number of Commandements, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> approues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 2. excommunicated the Emperor <hi>Leo,</hi> and diſcharged his people from obedience. 714.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> Emperour, reformed the Church of Images,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19944:12"/> although the Pope with-ſtood. 720.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſent <hi>Boniface, alias Wenefred,</hi> an Engliſh Monk, into diuers places, to preach the faith; he was martyred, as was one <hi>Willobrordus</hi> ſent before to preach by <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius Nauclere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prieſts mariages againſt, Purgatorie, Reliques, Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. <hi>Albertus Gallus, Clement,</hi> and <hi>Scotus,</hi> with many other learned men in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> withſtood the Biſhop, reformed <hi>Boniface</hi> in reliques, ſingle-life, Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Purgatorie, and Popes Supremacy. <hi>An. Chriſti,</hi> 735. The Pope is not yet ſetled in his neſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the fift Emperour, was vehement againſt Images. <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 741.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> the 2. abſolued <hi>Pippin,</hi> and the <hi>French,</hi> of their oath to the King, 752.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the 1. ſate ten yeeres and odde: He was vehement againſt the Emperour for Images, 758.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodor</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> maintained Images, 758.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> was againſt Images, 766.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the 1. gaue authority vnto <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, to chooſe the Pope, and to inueſt Biſhops, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, 772.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the fourth Emperor, was againſt Images, 777.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Raiginbald</hi> in <hi>Lumbardie</hi> would not obey the decree of <hi>Adrian,</hi> but kept their Wiues ſtill, 779.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the 3. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſate 20. yeeres: He was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned of the <hi>Romans</hi> for his cruelty, but <hi>Charles</hi> the Great pacified all, 796.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the 4. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſate one yere: He ſought
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19944:13"/> his confirmation of <hi>Lodowicke</hi> Emperour, 816.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> the 4. Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> would not take the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke, before he was confirmed of the Emperour, 827. <hi>Yet no Supremacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the 8. a woman Pope, ſate two yeeres &amp; one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. By generall conſent ſhee was choſen Pope, but not long after being great with childe by her ſeruant, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing for a while hid her great belly, in the end going to <hi>Lateran,</hi> betweene the Theater, which they call the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſe of <hi>Nero,</hi> and Saint <hi>Clement,</hi> falling into her throwes, ſhee was deliuered; hauing ſate two yeeres, and one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, and foure dayes: and was buried without honor. <hi>Anno</hi> 158. See <hi>Platina, Marianus, Scotus, Sigisbertus, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulphe, Volateran, Bergonius, Martin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benedict</hi> the 3. ſate three yeeres, being choſen, he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Office weeping, taking God to witneſſe that he was not worthy of ſuch a charge; he continued three dayes in faſting and prayer, deſiring God to giue him grace to gouerne the Church. <hi>Sup. Cron. Nauclere.</hi> He was depoſed from the Papacy, by the conſpiracy of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine wicked perſons, and a Cardinall vſurped the place but after againe he was reſtored. <hi>Eſtat. Church,</hi> 857.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas</hi> the 1. ſate ten yeres, he began to compel ſingle life, but could not preuaile; his decrees were greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. <hi>Huldrike</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Asburge</hi> in <hi>Almaigne,</hi> writ a worthy Epiſtle vnto him, <hi>Extant 859. Plat. Esta. Church,</hi> In his Epiſtle he puts him in minde of the like decree made by <hi>Gregory,</hi> who finding the fruit of his ſingle life, (namely, 6000. Infants heads found in a Pond, whither he ſent for Fiſh,) whereupon hee greatly repented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of his decree, which he confeſſed was the cauſe of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19944:13"/> ſo lamentable a murther, and ſo hee altered his former decree. <hi>Eſta Church,</hi> the Epiſtle at large, 859.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſecond, ſate ſixe yeeres: he was choſen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Emperour, and excuſing the matter, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was appeaſed, he was ſaluted Pope, <hi>Plat. Ro. Barus.</hi> after he granted the Election to the Citizens of <hi>Rome. Nauc.</hi> and <hi>Chron.</hi> Abb. 869. There was great diuiſion betweene the Greeke and Latine Church, onely for the primacy, and for the diuerſity of Ceremonies. <hi>Ro: Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus. Nauclere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth, ſate ten yeeres: he wrote Saint <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> life in foure Volumes, he gaue occaſion of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and warres, in chooſing of the Emperour. The Pope was committed to priſon, but by the helpe of his friends he eſcaped, and fledde into <hi>France,</hi> where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained a yeere. In the meane time <hi>Charles</hi> the third, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, was at <hi>Rome,</hi> and kept it. He ſent for the Pope to <hi>Rome,</hi> who returned, and ſo they raigned two yeeres together: <hi>Platina, Florent,</hi> and <hi>Ro. Barus.</hi> Finally, hee was poyſoned, or as ſome ſay, ſlaine with the blow of a mallet, vpon a conſpiracy made againſt him. <hi>Chron. Abb. Veſtper. Ro: Barus.</hi> 880.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin</hi> the ſecond, ſate one yeere and fiue moneths: he reſtored <hi>Formoſus</hi> Biſhop, diſgraded by his Predeceſſor; This Pope entred the Popedome by euill arts. <hi>Supple. Chron.</hi> 884.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the third, ſate one yeere and three moneths, he decreed the Emperor to be no more looked for in choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Pope, but that the Election of the Clergy ſhould be free: <hi>Diſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. Anno</hi> 886.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19944:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the ſixt, ſate ſeauen moneths and fifteene dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the fift, ſate ſixe yeeres and ten moneths.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Formoſus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Portuenſ:</hi> was appointed Pope, and ſate fiue yeeres and ſixe moneths, againſt the will of ſome Romans, which pretended that Cardinall <hi>Sergius</hi> was choſen, whereupon proceeded a great ſchiſme, cruell and ſcandelous, and indured a great time; this <hi>Formoſus</hi> bought the Papacy. <hi>Iohn le Maire. Supp. Cron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſixt, ſate fifteene dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the ſixt, ſate one yeere and ſixe moneths, hee euilly requited his predeceſſor <hi>Formoſus,</hi> who made him Biſhop of <hi>Anania,</hi> he condemned his acts, cauſed his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be taken out of his Tombe, threw his two fingers into <hi>Tiber,</hi> and buried his body in lay mens apparell: <hi>Plat. Naucler. Ro. Barus.</hi> At laſt he repented his faults, and became a Monke. <hi>Supp. Cron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Romaine,</hi> ſate three moneths and 22. dayes, hee eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the acts and decrees of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and diſanulled the acts and decrees of <hi>Stephen. Naucler. Anno</hi> 900.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodor</hi> the ſecond, ſate 22. dayes, he was a ſeditious man, and a very monſter in nature; he condemned <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> he reſtored the acts and fauourers of <hi>Formoſus: Naucler.</hi> 900.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the tenth, ſate two yeeres, hee was a ſedicious monſter, he reſtored <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and burned <hi>Stephens</hi> acts; he moued ſedition in <hi>Rome,</hi> and for feare fledde to <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna: Ro. Barus</hi> and <hi>Sigeber.</hi> 905.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the fourth, ſate three yeeres, he did nothing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of memory. <hi>Platt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19944:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the fift, ſate forty dayes; a Cardinall his familiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> impriſoned him, and by violence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Papacy. <hi>Leo</hi> dyed of griefe, 905.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Christopher</hi> ſate ſeauen moneths, he entered by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſo he loſt it; for he was depoſed, and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, was conſtrained to be a Monke, which was the onely refuge of the miſerable; wherein diſordered Church-men were detained, and incloſed in ſtrong Monaſteries, and there hee dyed. <hi>Naucler</hi> and <hi>Cron. Abb.</hi> 905.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> the third, ſate ſeauen yeeres, he condemned <hi>Formoſus</hi> acts, he tooke vp his body, and cut off his head, and threw him into <hi>Tyber:</hi> he begat <hi>Iohn</hi> the twelfth vpon a faire Whoore, Wife to <hi>Guido. Luithorandus. Anno</hi> 906.</p>
               <p>Note, <hi>Formoſus: Boniface</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Stephen</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Romaine, Theodorus</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Iohn</hi> the tenth, <hi>Bennet</hi> the fourth, <hi>Leo</hi> the fifth, <hi>Chriſtopher, Sergius</hi> the third; All theſe Popes condemned one anothers acts, ten ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding one another, aboue 20. yeeres: where is now their conſent they boaſt ſo of, a maine marke of their Church?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the third, ſate two yeeres and two moneths, an honeſt Pope: <hi>Supp.</hi> and <hi>Cron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laudo</hi> ſate fiue moneths, and more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the eleuenth, ſate thirteene yeeres and two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, he was Pope <hi>Sergius</hi> ſonne, and proued no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his Father, ſauing he proued a good Souldier; His owne Souldiers ſtifled him to death: <hi>Naucler.</hi> 917.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19944:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> ſate two yeeres, and twelue dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the twelfth, ſon to Pope <hi>Laudo,</hi> ſate foure yeeres, ten moneths, and fifteene dayes: he did nothing worthy memory, and of ſome is not numbred in the Catalogue of Popes: <hi>Supp. Chron.</hi> He obtained the Popedome by his Harlot <hi>Theodora:</hi> he was ſtrangled with a cuſhion by the Souldiers of <hi>Guido: Premonſtra</hi> 917.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the ſeauenth, ſate three yeeres and ſixe moneths. The Hereſie of the Anthropomorphites (which ſay, that God hath a corporall forme) was at that time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed. The Biſhop of <hi>Verone</hi> writ againſt it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the eight, ſate three yeeres, foure moneths, and twelue dayes; ſome ſay he was murthered in a ſedition, inſomuch as he was neuer publikely ſeene: <hi>Chron. Abb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martine</hi> the third, ſate three yeeres, ſixe moneths, and foureteene dayes; he was peaceable, and gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to repaire Temples, and to nouriſh the poore: ſaith <hi>Supp. Chron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Agapatus</hi> the ſecond, ſate nine yeeres, he did nothing memorable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the thirteenth, ſate nine yeeres, and three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths. This mans Father <hi>Abaric,</hi> being of the greateſt power of <hi>Rome,</hi> cauſed the nobleſt and chiefe Rulers to promiſe and ſweare, to chooſe after the death of <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patus,</hi> his eldeſt ſonne, this <hi>Iohn:</hi> He was a vile monſter in life, he committed inceſt with both his Siſters, and his Fathers Concubines; at Dice he would call to the Diuel, and drinke to the Diuell, he maintained a publike ſtewes. He was depoſed by the Emperour in a Counſell; was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19944:15"/> againe placed, and ſoone after was taken againe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, and was ſlayne by the husband of the wife, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 960. <hi>Plat. Ro. Baras. Chron. Sigesb. Naucler.</hi> and <hi>Ioh. Maire:</hi> Others ſay, that the diuell brake his necke <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton Chro. Faſci Baronius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the fift ſate ſixe moneths and fiue dayes: Hee was depoſed by the Emperour, and baniſhed into <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,</hi> where hee dyed, and <hi>Leo</hi> placed in his roome: <hi>Anno 963. Naucler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the eight ſate one yeere and foure moneths: Hee eſtabliſhed to the Emperour, the chooſing of the Pope, with inueſting. <hi>Naucler.</hi> and <hi>Diſt. 63. cap. in Synod.</hi> 964.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the fourteenth ſate ſixe yeeres, eleuen months, and ten dayes: He was impriſoned by the Citizens, and <hi>Peter,</hi> Prouoſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> but was reſtored by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt; and <hi>Peter</hi> was deliuered to the Popes deuotion, who gaue him to the tormentors hands, who vnapparrelled him, cut off his beard, and ſet him vpon an Aſſe, his face to ward the tayle, and his hands bound vnder the tayle, and ſo was led through the Towne, and beaten with rods: after he was brought to priſon, and finally, was baniſhed into <hi>Almaine. Naucler. Volateran. Anno</hi> 965.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the ſixt ſate one yeere, and ſixe moneths: Hee was put in priſon at Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> wherein he was ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled by <hi>Cynthius. Naucler.</hi> 973.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeauenth ſate ſeauen months: the greateſt in <hi>Rome</hi> conſpired againſt him, for hee entred by euill meanes. He pilled the moſt precious treaſures of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19944:16"/> Church of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and fledde into <hi>Constantinople,</hi> where he continued eight moneths, &amp; hauing turned all into ſiluer, he returned into <hi>Rome.</hi> In his abſence they lifted vp one, whom they called <hi>Iohn</hi> the fifteenth: Hee ſate eight moneths: But <hi>Boniface</hi> corrupted the vileſt and wicked perſons of <hi>Rome.</hi> This done, he tooke Pope <hi>Iohn,</hi> and put out his eyes, and made him die with hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> and ſo poſſeſt the place, but he died incontinently after of a ſodayne death, and his corps was drawne with a cord by his feete through the ſtreetes, and pierced with pikes by the <hi>Romanes:</hi> but the Clarks buried him. <hi>Naucler. Ro. Barus. Cro. Abb. Anno</hi> 976.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the ſeuenth ſate eight yeeres and ſixe moneths: he did nothing worthy memory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the fifteenth died in priſon, as before: in <hi>Bonif.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſixteenth ſate foure moneths: for giuing the goods of the Church to his parents, friends and allies, he was hated of the Clergie, and people, and was inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> where he died of hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. <hi>Supp. Cron Ro. Barus.</hi> 976.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſeuenteenth ſate tenne yeeres: for feare of <hi>Creſcentius</hi> the <hi>Roman</hi> Rebell, he fled to <hi>Hitruria,</hi> cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing aide of the Emperour, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the fift was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in his roome. 987.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the fift ſate three yeeres: He was depoſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Emperours departure, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the eighteenth was placed in his roome: but the Emperour killed both the new Popes, <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Creſcentius,</hi> and placed <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie.</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19944:16"/> 995. and ſo was a Schiſme of two Popes. <hi>Naucler. Supp. Cron. &amp; Plat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond ſate foure yeeres: Hee was a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitian, and came to the Seate by the Art of the Diuell, vnto whom hee had done homage, that all his affaires might goe after his wiſh. He had moſt curious bookes of Magicke, which he got from a Philoſopher, by the helpe of his daughter; and fearing to be ſurprized of it, he vowed himſelfe to the Diuell, vpon condition he would bring him to <hi>France,</hi> and at laſt he came to be Pope: And deſiring of the Diuell to know how long he ſhould be Pope, the Diuell anſwered; vntill hee ſayd Maſſe at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Then he followed his delights: but on a day in Lent celebrating the Maſſe in the Church of the holy Croſſe of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> he was ſodainely taken with a great feuer, &amp;c. and ſodainely hee heard a great tumult of Diuells in his preſence, &amp;c. and ſurprized with feare, hee ſent for his Cardinalls, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his body ſhould be hewen in peeces; but ſpecially, ſuch of his members whereby hee had worſhipped the Diuell, and then that all ſhould be put in a Cart, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what place ſoeuer the Horſes which drew the Cart went, and ſhould ſtay, there he ſhould be buried. The horſes, without any direction, carried his body into the Church of <hi>Laterane,</hi> where he was layd in a Sepulchre. And at this day his Sepulchre is a pronoſtike token of a Popes death. 999. <hi>Ro. Barus. Suppl. Cron. Bermo</hi> and <hi>Naucler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the twentith ſate foure yeeres and fiue moneths: He was ſuſpected to haue made away his predeceſſour.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Silueſter</hi> vntill <hi>Hildebrand</hi> theſe Popes gaue
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19944:17"/> themſelues to diabolicall Arts: He died not without ſuſpition of poyſon. <hi>Naucler.</hi> 1006.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sergius</hi> the fourth ſate two yeeres and ſixe moneths: He entred by Art Magicke. 1006.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the eight ſate twelue yeeres: Hee was depoſed by the Cardinalls and people of <hi>Rome,</hi> and at the length got his place againe; and ſoone after dyed. <hi>Supp. Chron.</hi> He appeared after his death vnto a Biſhop his familiar, vpon a blacke horſe, and complayning of his torments, ſhewing how he might, by Suffrages, Maſſes, and Almſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds be diſcharged from Purgatory. <hi>Anno 1010. Plat. Naucler. Ro. Barus. Supp. Chron. Faſci. temporum,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>Note wee here, the Pope that can giue Indulgences for twenty thouſand yeeres, and deliuer what ſoules he will out of Purgatory, cannot now eaſe himſelfe. <hi>Quomodo conſtat?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty one ſate tenne yeeres: Hee crowned <hi>Conrad</hi> Emperour; and therefore hee defended him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Romans. Theophilact,</hi> alias <hi>Benedict</hi> the ninth. <hi>Iohn, Gratian, Laurence, Maſſican, Brazutus, Heldibrand:</hi> all Coniurers ruled at <hi>Rome, Anno</hi> 1031.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the ninth ſate tenne yeeres, foure moneths, and nine dayes. <hi>Supp. Chron.</hi> He was an horrible Coniurer, who by inchantment hauing got the Popedome to his two Vnckles, <hi>Benedict,</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> now himſelfe obtained it. He ſtirred vp <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Hungary</hi> againſt the Emperour <hi>Henry:</hi> Hee choſe another Pope to him, <hi>Silueſter</hi> the third; and ſolde the Popedome to a third, <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſixt, <note place="margin">Three Popes.</note> and ſo three were Popes together; but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19944:17"/> depoſed them all, and placed <hi>Clement</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. 1033.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the third, Emperour, called <hi>Niger,</hi> cut off the Schiſme of the Popes. 1041.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Silueſter</hi> the third ſate fiftie and fiue dayes: after <hi>Benet</hi> was depriued hee was choſen Pope, by gifts and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. <hi>Supp. Chron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſixt ſate two yeeres and ſixe moneths: In the time of the former Schiſme hee was adiudged a Symoniacke, and Homicide, yet he bought the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Benet. Ro. Barus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the ſecond ſate nine moneths: After the foure aboue-named were depoſed: He was choſen in ful coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: Hee crowned <hi>Henry</hi> the third Emperour, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he departed from <hi>Rome,</hi> conſtrayned the <hi>Romanes,</hi> by oath, to renounce their right of Election, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more medling therein hereafter, to auoyd Schiſme, and Scandals, which commonly ariſe of ſuch Elections. <hi>Naucler.</hi> The <hi>Romanes,</hi> after his departure, forgetting their oath, impriſoned this Pope, after he had gouerned nine moneths. Some ſay that <hi>Damaſus</hi> his Succeſſour was Author thereof: others ſay, <hi>Gerard Braſier</hi> and <hi>Heldibrand,</hi> a man expert in poyſoning. <hi>Benno.</hi> In his time men forged Viſions and Miracles, to eſtabliſh the Sacrament of the Maſſe, which then was called the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Altar: this Pope was poyſoned ſoone after the Emperours departure. <hi>Naucler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Damaſus</hi> the ſecond ſate three and twenty dayes: He entred by force, for he occupied the Popedome without
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19944:18"/> Election, either ſuffrage of people, or Clergie. <hi>Chron. Ro. Barus.</hi> He poyſoned <hi>Clement,</hi> and himſelfe was poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by <hi>Brazutus. Anno</hi> 1048.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the ninth ſate ſixe yeeres: He being ſent by the Emperour, reiecting the Election, was choſen by the people through <hi>Hildebrand. Plat.</hi> He condemned <hi>Berin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius</hi> doctrine. He was poiſoned by <hi>Brazutus,</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedict</hi> the ninth got his place againe, and dyed; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appeared in the likeneſſe of a Beare. 1049.</p>
               <p>Popescannot ſaue themſelues from Purgatorie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor</hi> the ſecond: The people of <hi>Rome</hi> fearing the Emperours diſpleaſure in chooſing of a new Pope (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing before forgotten their oath) ſent <hi>Hildebrand</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Emperour, to chooſe a Pope, and in the meane while, <hi>Victor</hi> was choſen, not ſo voluntarily, as to pleaſe the Emperour, in electing an <hi>Almaine,</hi> borne of <hi>Bauier:</hi> he ruled two yeeres and three moneths: he was poyſoned by <hi>Brazutus.</hi> 1054.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen</hi> the ninth ſate ten moneths, after other foure moneths, hee brought <hi>Millane</hi> vnder the obedience of <hi>Rome,</hi> which from the Apoſtles time was free. <hi>Plat. Ro. Barus. Naucler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the tenth ſate nine moneths: the <hi>Romanes</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted with ſiluer, elected him againſt the Cannons, though the Glergie were againſt it. But he was conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to giue ouer the Popedome, and led a priuate life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond ſate three yeeres and ſix months: he called a Counſell at <hi>Rome,</hi> where they decreed <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. Nicholas</hi> cauſed <hi>Berengarius</hi> to recant. He
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19944:18"/> was poyſoned by <hi>Brazutus. Hildebrand</hi> expelled <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> from the Popedome, becauſe he ſaid he entred not in by the doore, but by force, and gifts. <hi>Plat.</hi> So were two Popes together vntill <hi>Benedict</hi> reſigned. 1058.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond ſate eleuen yeeres: He had <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalus</hi> choſen againſt him, who comming to <hi>Rome</hi> with a ſtrong band; <hi>Alexander</hi> met him with the <hi>Romans,</hi> and the battell was hard and ſharpe, where was a great ſlaughter, where <hi>Alexander</hi> got the day. The warre betwixt them continued two yeeres. <hi>Candalus</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to yeelde, and to redeeme his life with ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred markes. <hi>Iohn le maire</hi> 1062.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> was buffeted by <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> was impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; died, about 1074. Others, 1062. <hi>Benno Cardinal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeauenth, before called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> ſate twelue yeeres, and one moneth: rather a monſter in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then a man. Hee poyſoned ſeauen or eight Popes by the ſeruice of <hi>Brazutus,</hi> the ſooner to come to the Papacie; hee vſurped the Papacie without Emperour, Clergie, or people. Hee cruelly hand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the family of <hi>Quintius,</hi> who had impriſoned him; he cauſed the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour three dayes to attend bare foote for abſolution. He ſtirred <hi>Rodulph</hi> againſt him, and two more, one after the death of another: hee vſed to carry about him a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious booke of Nigromancy, which one day forgetting, hee ſent two of his truſty ſeruants, in ſuch matters, to fetch it him (being now at the doore of the <hi>Lateran</hi>) with a ſpeciall charge, not to looke into it. But they of a curious minde opened it and read in the Booke; and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainely the Angells of Sathan preſented themſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lues, the multitude whereof, and the horrour of them, brought
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19944:19"/> theſe two young men almoſt out of their wits, and as themſelues reported, theſe euill ſpirits inſiſted ſtrongly, ſaying; Wherefore haue you called vs? Command vs quickely what you will haue vs to doe, elſe we will fall vpon you, &amp;c. One of the young men anſwered, Caſt vs downe theſe walls ſtrait-way, and ſhewing them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine high walls, in a moment, the euill ſpirits threw them to the earth. They thus terrified, and trembling, almoſt without breath, came to their maſter: this wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Benno,</hi> a Cardinall, who was in this time. This Pope practiſed treaſons and murther againſt the Emperour, inſomuch as hee ſought to haue ſlaine him euen in the Church as he ſhould haue been at his prayers. He prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed often in the Church of Saint <hi>Marke</hi> in mount <hi>Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine.</hi> The Pope ſuborned one, promiſing great ſummes of money, to lay great ſtones vpon the beames of the Church, ouer the place where the Emperour vſually prayed, and to be let downe vpon the Emperour to cruſh him to death: but this wretched creature remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a ſtone too heauie for him, fell downe with it vpon the pauement of the Church, &amp; it burſt him all aſunder. <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Port</hi> the Popes Secretary, openly in the Pulpet confeſſed <hi>Hildebrand</hi> to haue done ſuch a thing, and we alſo as deceiuers ſhould be burned aliue; giuing to vnderſtand, that which he had done of the Sacrament of the Supper of our Lord, that is, the decree of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation: whereof <hi>Hildebrand</hi> commanding <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> of a certaine thing (as of old the Painims did of their Idols) hee caſt the Hoaſt into the fire, becauſe it gaue him no anſwere, though the Cardinalls ſpake againſt it. Thus farre <hi>Benno</hi> a Cardinall.</p>
               <p>Note a beginning of the fruits of that curſed decree of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19944:19"/> Tranſubſtantiation applied vnto charmes and inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Moreouer, as he roſe vp from his ſeate to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the Emperor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, the ſeate (late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made of new and ſtrong wood) of it ſelfe brake into many peeces in terrible manner. <hi>Benno.</hi> He decreed ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle life to the Clergie, where-about hee moued maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous tragedies, yet in <hi>Almaine,</hi> and in <hi>Fraunce</hi> were twenty foure Biſhops and more, which together with their Clergie, were married, and defended, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly maintained their marriage. He commanded the vowe of Chaſtitie: hee ordayned the offering of the Maſſe. He was depoſed, and fled to <hi>Salerne. An.</hi> 1086. where he died in exile. <hi>Abb. Veſp. Benno Balenus</hi> poiſoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the third was choſen Ante-pope to <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth; ſo were two Popes together ſixeteene yeares: he ſate three yeares and fiue moneths. <hi>Plat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Victor</hi> the third was made Pope, not by election of Cardinalls, nor people of <hi>Rome,</hi> but was there inthroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, by <hi>Mathilde, Gregories</hi> louer onely, and the <hi>Normans</hi> of that faction: hee ſate foure moneths. He entred and intended to follow the example of his predeceſſour <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie,</hi> in mouing of warres, and againſt the Emperour, and Pope <hi>Clement:</hi> he died of poiſon, which was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Challice by his Subdeacon, as he ſung Maſſe. <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Contract. Carſulan. praemonſt.</hi> 1086.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſecond, choſen by <hi>Mathilde</hi> onely, againſt the will of the Emperour, ſate twelue yeares, foure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, and nineteene dayes. He was <hi>Hildebrands</hi> famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, he watred, &amp; cauſed to grow his pernitious ſeeds. He excommunicated the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> and <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19944:20"/> the third, becauſe he had bin choſen by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: ſome call him the <hi>Perturber of the World.</hi> He would abſolue none excommunicated by <hi>Hildebrand:</hi> and fearing to fall into danger of his life, he went ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the Towne, and celebrated many Synods at <hi>Melph,</hi> two at <hi>Troy,</hi> three at <hi>Plaiſance,</hi> foure at <hi>Clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> fiue at <hi>Toures,</hi> in which he confirmed the acts of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> and made new Eccleſiaſticall ordinances, to fortifie the Papacy. This Pope curſed the Emperour, and the Ante-pope <hi>Clement,</hi> and he him againe. Hee heard <hi>Anſelme</hi> againſt <hi>William Rufus</hi> 1088.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paſchal</hi> the ſecond ſate eighteene-yeeres, and ſixe moneths, and ſeauen dayes: He followed the ſteppes of <hi>Hildebrand:</hi> He imployed all his time in warres: he put from their dignities all Eccleſiaſticall perſons which had been ordained by the Emperor. He aſſembled a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell at <hi>Rome.</hi> 1101. becauſe of an opinion of a Biſhop of <hi>Florence,</hi> touching Antichriſt already borne. <hi>Sabellicus.</hi> Seeing ſo many miſchiefes committed in the Church, he prohibited Miniſters marriages. Hee renewed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeauenth, and <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſecond, againſt the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, cauſing the ſonne to take vp Armes againſt his father, an inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane, and horrible crueltie. The ſonne moſt vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally beſieged his father, tooke him traiterouſly, diſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him of all his Imperiall dignities, and made him die a poore miſerable man, in great captiuitie and heauines: and all at the inſtigation of Chriſts pretended Vicar. Yet this Papall monſter, not appeaſed with his death, commanded by his Letters, that his body ſhould be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buried, and caſt out of the Church, &amp;c. and to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19944:20"/> for fiue yeeres of Sepulture. <hi>Euſeb. Chron.</hi> Hee diſpoyled the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rauenna</hi> of his lands, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying them to his owne profit: and after commanded the Archbiſhop of the ſame place to be taken vp, who had beene choſen Pope by the Emperour, in the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeuenth, ſixe yeares after hee had laid in the Sepulchre. The Emperor and the Pope accorded, yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Henry</hi> the fift inueſtitures: but after he reuoked it and excommunicated the Emperour. But the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour comming to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pope fled to <hi>Apulia,</hi> where he dyed. <hi>Anno</hi> 1114.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gelaſius</hi> the ſecond ſate one yeere and ſix months, was choſen without the Emperor: he was impriſond by <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius</hi> a great man of <hi>Rome,</hi> but he was deliuered by the people: the Emperor ſent his Armie to <hi>Rome.</hi> The Pope fearing, fled to <hi>Gayette.</hi> The Emperor created another Pope called <hi>Gregorie</hi> the eight, the eighteenth Schiſme of two Popes. <hi>Gelacius</hi> condemned the Emperour, and the Ante-pope. <hi>R. Barus. Gelacius</hi> came ſecretly to <hi>Rome;</hi> hee was knowne, and hardly eſcaped into <hi>France. Supp. Chron.</hi> 1118. He dyed of a plurifie at <hi>Clugni,</hi> where he was buried.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calixt</hi> the ſecond ſate fiue yeeres: he was choſen by the Cardinalls. The Ante-pope came againſt him. He was ouercome in battell; and being taken by Pope <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixt,</hi> hee was ſet vpon a Cammell, his face towards the taile, and ſo made him goe, and after impriſoned him. <hi>Iohn le Maire. Faſc. temporum.</hi> 1119.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Honorius</hi> the ſecond ſate fiue yeares, and two mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths: <hi>Arnulph</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Lions</hi> had at that time a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19944:21"/> ſingular gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce in preaching; and after he had preached in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and came to <hi>Italie,</hi> he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee rebuked too ſharpely the vices, delights, and pompes of the Church-men, hee was ſlaine. The Pope ſeemed to be grieued at it, yet made he no great ſearch for the murtherers. <hi>Plat. Sabellicus. Bonifac. Simo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Popes Legate <hi>Iohn,</hi> was taken in bed with a whoore at <hi>London. Grafton.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſecond ſate foureteene yeeres: hee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt <hi>Roger</hi> the Norman; but <hi>Innocent</hi> was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in battell, and led away priſoner: while he was in priſon, the <hi>Romans</hi> elected another, but <hi>Innocent</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with <hi>Roger,</hi> hee was conſtrained to goe into <hi>France</hi> for ſuccour, where he held two Counſells: after he returned towards the Emperour, who promiſed his aide, and ſo he returned into <hi>Italie. Anaclete</hi> the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pope hearing thereof, ſtole away all the treaſure and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the Church, to wage them which were of his band: He dyed with griefe, and his Cardinalls craued pardon. Thus two Popes continued ſixe yeeres. 1136.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celestine</hi> the ſecond ſate fiue months, and eight daies: he died of the peſtilence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucius</hi> the ſecond ſate one yeere: hee willing to take away the dignity of the <hi>Patritian,</hi> died of the peſtilence. <hi>Supp. Chron. Faſci. temporum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eugenius</hi> the third ſate eight yeeres: hauing excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated certaine <hi>Romans,</hi> hee was conſtrained to flee into <hi>France,</hi> 1145. comming againe he was honourably receiued; but he ſoone after dyed at <hi>Tyber,</hi> going to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create himſelfe. Hee was brought to <hi>Rome,</hi> and buried
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19944:21"/> in the Temple of Saint <hi>Peter. Supp. Cron.</hi> 1145.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> againſt the impietie of the Popes, and the Eccleſiaſticall ſort: ſee his 67. Sermon, where he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them the Miniſters of Antechriſt. <hi>Item</hi> 57. in his booke to <hi>Eugenius. Item</hi> in the 33. Sermon vpon the <hi>Canticles,</hi> he often ſaith that Prelates are but Pilats. He reproueth <hi>Eugenius,</hi> that leauing the word of God, hee aduanced humane Traditions. And <hi>Hugo Cardinalis,</hi> in his Poſtill vpon Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> alleadgeth that <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth in a certaine place: It ſeemeth, O good Ieſus, that all the vniuerſity of Chriſtians haue conſpired againſt thee, and they are the chiefe of the conſpiration which obtaine the Primacie of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anastaſius</hi> ſate one yeere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth ſate fiue yeeres and ſixe moneths: he would not goe to the Church of <hi>Lateran</hi> to be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, vntill firſt <hi>Arnold</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Brixe</hi> was caſt out of the Towne, who oppoſed himſelfe againſt the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Ciuill things, and Temporall Sword, which the Clergie had vſurped. Hee was angry with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour for holding his left ſtirrope at his lighting. Hee ſtirred vp all <hi>Italie</hi> to rebell againſt him, for receiuing homage of his owne Biſhops. He was troubled of the <hi>Romans</hi> for their auncient Liberties. <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Salisburie</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chartyrs,</hi> was a worthy man: Hee reproued many things in the Clergie, and Popes, and being very familiar with <hi>Adrian,</hi> he was heard to ſay to <hi>Iohn,</hi> That there were many Popes which rather ſucceeded <hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> in murther, then Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in feeding the ſheepe. He excommunicated <hi>William</hi> King of <hi>Sicilie,</hi> and <hi>Pouill.</hi> Finally, he was choaked with a flie: he ſayd, the life of a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19944:22"/> Pope was moſt miſerable. 1154.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the third ſate about two and twenty yeers: He was choſen by one halfe of the Cardinalls, and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> on the other ſide; and ſo continued a Schiſme of two Popes twenty yeeres, euen all the dayes of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander:</hi> For after <hi>Victor,</hi> came <hi>Paſchalis</hi> the third, then <hi>Calixt,</hi> laſtly, <hi>Innocent:</hi> vnto theſe all the Biſhops of the Empire were ſworne. <hi>Alexander</hi> granted the auncient Liberties to the <hi>Romans.</hi> He cauſed all <hi>Italie</hi> to rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Emperour: hee troade vpon the Emperours necke. Hee defended <hi>Becket</hi> againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, King of <hi>England</hi> 1160. Hee ſeeking the Emperours death (while he was buſied with the Turke) ſent a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Turke, with the liuely Image of the King, to ſeeke to ſlay him. The Emperour with his Chaplaine on a hote day going to waſh him, was ſurprized by an ambuſh of the Sultans, and brought before the Turke, where he fained himſelfe to be the Emperours Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine; but the Turke ſhewing him his Image, and the Popes Letters, he confeſſed the truth, and deſired fauor: at length the Turke ſent him away, vnder certaine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions agreed betwixt them. The Emperour returning, aſſigned a day at <hi>Noremberg,</hi> and aſſembled his Court, declared the Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> his treaſon, ſhewing his Letters, and the Image. Briefly, euery one promiſed his helpe to pay his ranſome, and to doe iuſtice vpon the ſaid <hi>Alexander.</hi> The Pope vnderſtanding his treaſon was come to light, and what the Emperour intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, he fled from <hi>Rome</hi> in the habite of his coole, and came to <hi>Venice.</hi> The <hi>Venetians</hi> maintained the Pope. The Emperour ſent Embaſſadours to demand <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander;</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19944:22"/> finally, he ſent his ſonne <hi>Otho:</hi> the youth led with his Company, gaue battell: he loſt the victory, and was taken priſoner; which the Pope ſeeing, would not agree with the Emperour, except he came to <hi>Venice,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the meanes he would offer. The Emperour to helpe his ſonne, came to <hi>Venice.</hi> The Pope would not abſolue him of excommunication, vntill he preſented himſelfe at the doore of Saint <hi>Markes</hi> Church: When he came thither, the Pope commanded him, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of al the people, to caſt himſelfe vpon the ground, and demand pardon; which he doing, the Pope ſet his foot vpon the Emperours necke, and preſſing it downe, ſayd: <hi>Thou ſhalt goe vpon the Aſpe and Baſiliske, and tread vnder thy feete, the Lyon and the Dragon.</hi> The Emperour anſwered; This was not ſaid to thee, but to <hi>Peter.</hi> But the Pope ſtepping againe vpon his neck, anſwered, Both to me, and to <hi>Peter.</hi> The Emperour fearing ſome dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, held his peace; and ſo was abſolued, and vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions agreed. <hi>Eſtate of the Church,</hi> and <hi>Plat.</hi> Now let the world iudge, whether this be Chriſts Vicar, <hi>Peters</hi> true Succeſſour, a ſeruant of ſeruants, or a Luciferian proude Pope, the ſonne of perdition, and Antechriſt himſelfe, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itteth in the Temple of God, and boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe aboue all that is called God. 1180.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lucius</hi> the third ſate foure yeeres, and two moneths: while he went about to expell the Conſuls and Patricij of <hi>Rome,</hi> he was caſt out, and withdrew himſelfe to <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice:</hi> Such as tooke his part, had their eyes put out; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were ſet vpon Aſſes, with their faces towards the tayle, and ignominiouſly handled. <hi>Platin.</hi> Hee dyed at <hi>Veron.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19944:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrban</hi> the third ſate one yeere, and ſixe months. <hi>Sup.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the eight ſate fiftie ſeauen dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the third ſate three yeeres, and ſixe months: he made a Decretall againſt all ſuch Prieſts as celebrated Maſſe in woodden veſſells, and with common bread. Heere is nothing reſpected but outward things, and the commandement of God neglected. Note againe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread was now in vſe in the Lords Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the third ſate ſixe yeeres: Hee crowned the Emperour with his feet, ſitting in his Pontifical Chaire, and holding the Imperiall Crowne betweene his feete; and the Emperour bowing downe his head, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Empreſſe, receiued it from his feet: and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately hee kickes it off againe to the ground, in token that he had power (if he ſo deſerue) to depoſe him. The Cardinalls ſtanding round about, reuerently tooke it vp, and ſet it on their heads againe. <hi>Baronius. Ranulph. Mysterie of Iniquitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the third ſate eighteene yeeres: he abſolued the Princes from their oath to the Emperour, cauſed them to chooſe <hi>Otho</hi> the fourth, and after excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>Otho</hi> alſo. This Pope added a very dangerous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence vnto the Articles of the Faith, that is, Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, as a thirteenth Article of the Faith. See the Decretalls. <hi>Tit. 1. De Summa Trinitate &amp; fide Apostolica. cap. Firmiter credimus.</hi> This Decretall was made in the yeere of Chriſt 1215. and promulged in the Counſell of <hi>Lateran.</hi> Hee made another Decree of the Cannon of the Maſſe, and commanded it to be receiued, as from the Apoſtles: Thus they place in the roome of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19944:23"/> of the Apoſtles, their owne Decrees. Hee alſo commaunded confeſſion in the Prieſts eare, at the leaſt once a yeare. See Decretal. <hi>Tit. 38. cap. Omnes vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſexus.</hi> He dyed at <hi>Pice. Anno</hi> 1216.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Honorius</hi> the third ſate tenne yeeres, and ſeauen mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths: he excommunicated the Emperour: hee raiſed the French againſt the Earle of <hi>Theloſſa,</hi> for fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Albingenſes.</hi> He was denyed in <hi>France</hi> the exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of two Prebends in euery Church, and two Monkes in euery Abbey 1216. Hee confirmed the order of the <hi>Iacobines,</hi> which his predeceſſors had refuſed to do; and confirmed the order of the <hi>Mendicants.</hi> He comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Hoſte ſhould be kept in a place by it ſelfe, and well incloſed. When the Hoſte was lifted vp, the people to do reuerence, and bowe to it; and alſo, when it was carried to the ſicke. He confirmed the order of Saint <hi>Francis. Faſci. temporum.</hi> Thus the fulneſſe of infection is come into the Church by the foure plagues of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Monkes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ninth ſate foureteene yeeres, and three moneths: This Pope heaped vp Decretalls, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to be kept through all Chriſtendome, in Schooles and Iudgement. Thus the word of God is ſet aſide for their traditions. <hi>Peter de Vienna</hi> complained, That all the world cannot fill the inſatiabilitie of the Pope; That the turpitudes of the Clergie are ſo great, and enormious, as ſhame forbiddeth to ſpeake thereof. Hee alſo maintained, that the Pope, neither by diuine, nor humane right, hath any power of the Sword. The Pope excommunicated him. <hi>William</hi> the Gold-ſmith at this time, ſheweth that the Pope is Antichriſt, <hi>Rome Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19944:24"/> the Prelates, members of Antichriſt. <hi>Caeſarius 10. Diſtinct.</hi> 3. of his Dialogues. The Pope was driuen out of <hi>Rome</hi> by the <hi>Romans.</hi> He curſed the Emperour <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derike</hi> for not going to the holy Land: and the ſecond time, for puniſhing Rebells, and receiued 12000. oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of gold, for abſoluing him. <hi>Vide Plat.</hi> and the <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Iniquitie. pa.</hi> 360. He curſed the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church, and they him againe: he plagued the Clergie of <hi>England</hi> by exactions, foure markes of euery Church: the fift part of euery Eccleſiaſticall perſon: 10000. markes for maintaining of the warres againſt the Emperour: he ſtirred vp his ſonne againſt him. He wrote to the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens,</hi> not to agree with him. He fell out with the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Columna,</hi> becauſe he would not doe a vile meſſage to the Emperour, ſaying; I hold thee not hence-forth for Cardinall: Nor I thee for Pope, ſayd <hi>Columna:</hi> and ſo he departed: <hi>Math. Pariſ.</hi> See the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity.</hi> fol. 304. <hi>Gregorie</hi> afflicted with ſo many miſchiefes, fell ſicke, and dyed with ſorrow and griefe. 1241.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the fourth ſate eighteen dayes: was poiſoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth ſate eleuen yeeres, and ſixe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths: He canonized many Saints, made much of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Friers. Hee preſcribed the Emperour <hi>Frederike,</hi> and <hi>Conrade,</hi> and then commanded <hi>William</hi> to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen againſt him. He exacted in <hi>England</hi> the third of all Church-goods: and the yeerely fruits of vacant Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and halfe of all Non-reſidences: and all the inteſtate Eccleſiaſticall. Againe, of ſome Prieſts, fifteene, of ſome tenne, of ſome, fiue able men, furniſhed with horſe and harneſſe to the warres, for one whole yeere: beſides 10000. markes, and after 70000. markes to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19944:24"/> this warre, in deſpite of King <hi>Henry;</hi> beſides <hi>Peter</hi>-pence: 60000. markes yeerely of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ent Clarkes: He reuoked Friers priuiledges, excommunicated them, and all religious perſons. The Emperour ſayde (fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing what would follow when hee was choſen Pope;) I haue loſt a Cardinall my friend, and haue choſen a Pope mine enemie: <hi>Plat.</hi> So honours change manners; and the very pride of the place makes them forget all duty to God, and man. He dyed miſerably at <hi>Naples,</hi> ſooner than he thought. <hi>Naucler.</hi> 1250.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the fourth ſate ſeauen yeeres: he was ſet vp againſt <hi>Conrade</hi> the Emperour: hee reuoked the acts of <hi>Innocent,</hi> condemned the Bookes of <hi>Gulielmus de San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto amore,</hi> written againſt Begging Friers: <hi>Plat.</hi> popiſh Clergie, calling the Pope Antechriſt. He loſt his armie in <hi>Nicrea,</hi> and comming to <hi>Viterbe,</hi> he dyed there 1261.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Siluester</hi> the ſecond that diuelliſh Magitian, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till this time, the Popes haue reigned as incarnate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, in all trumperies, deceits, oppreſſion of the good, and manifeſt tyrannies, and haue tormented by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall furies, the greateſt monarkes; <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth and fift, the ſecond <hi>Fredericke,</hi> and other princes of the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrbane</hi> the fourth ſate three yeeres and one moneth: hee raiſed vp warres againſt <hi>Maufroy,</hi> and after againſt <hi>Conradin,</hi> and ouercame them both, and ſo obtayned the lands; but the end was miſerable: for the <hi>Sicillians,</hi> after the yeere 1282. rebelled againſt him, and ſlew all his French army in an euening ſodainely, and opened their women great with childe, and caſt away their fruit, that they, nor none of that generation might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19944:25"/> This occaſion was afterward commonly called, the <hi>Euenſong</hi> of <hi>Sicilie:</hi> This Pope dyed at <hi>Peruſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the fourth ſate three yeers and nine months: He had wife and children. Hee was the King of <hi>France</hi> his Chancellor. After his wifes death, he was Biſhop of <hi>Pauy:</hi> after Archbiſhop of <hi>Narbon:</hi> after Cardinall, and was choſen Pope. Hee demanded a certaine tenth in <hi>Almayne. Iohn,</hi> Gloſſator of the Decree, and Prouoſt of Saint <hi>Stephen de Alberſtate,</hi> oppoſed himſelfe againſt it, and appealed to the next Counceil, for the which hee was excommunicated of the Pope, and depriued of his office. <hi>Sea of Hiſtories. Clement</hi> had a nephew which held three Benefices; he conſtrained him to forſake two of them. <hi>Naucler.</hi> He died at <hi>Viterbe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the tenth ſate foure yeeres: he aſſembled a Counſell at <hi>Lions,</hi> where was agreed the tenth part of the goods of the Church, to be giuen for ſixe yeeres, to maintaine the warres for the conqueſt of the lands be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas. He labored to bring the Greeke Church vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> but all in vaine; ſo as he is not vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, nor his Succeſſors. 1272. He came to <hi>Aretinum,</hi> where he died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the fift ſate ſixe moneths, and two dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the fift ſate fortie dayes: he died at <hi>Viterbe.</hi> 1276. before hee was conſecrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the two and twentieth ſate eight moneths, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing himſelfe long life, foretold by the Starres, as hee affirmed it, but in the preſence of his people, a new Vault, <hi>Valerius</hi> calleth it a playing Hall; <hi>Stella,</hi> a rich
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19944:25"/> and precious chamber, which he had built in his pallace at <hi>Viterbie,</hi> fell the fourth day following ſodainely vpon him, in the yeere 1277. and the ſeauenth day after the ſayd ruine, he was found miſerably ſlaine, betwixt the ſtones and the timber, and was buried in the great Church. Here the Pope found by experience the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of his diuination. At this time was the doctrine of the <hi>Waldois,</hi> holding but two Sacraments, baptiſme and the Communion: The Maſſe an abhominable and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable thing, and therefore to be aboliſhed: All hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane tradition to be reiected, as not neceſſary to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: againſt many other toyes of Popery; againſt the Popes Supremacie; called <hi>Rome</hi> very <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Pope the fountaine of all euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third ſate foure yeeres: He tranſported to himſelfe the dignity of the Senator of <hi>Rome.</hi> He made a Parke for Hares and Conies, for his pleaſure to hunt in. He gaue much to his nephew, or rather baſtard, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Barthand,</hi> that hee tooke from others by force: as ſome ſay, hee ingendered vpon a Concubine of his baſtards, a monſter, whoſe haire and nayles were like a Beares. See <hi>Iohn de Naion,</hi> in his Inſtitutions of <hi>Beda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as hee was determined to preferre the houſe of the <hi>Vrſins,</hi> of which houſe he was, and therefore had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be paynted the pictures of Beares in the Pallace, being in the towne of <hi>Sutry,</hi> hee was taken with an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy, of which he died ſodainly, and without ſpeech. <hi>Anno</hi> 1291.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin</hi> the fourth ſate two yeeres and eight months: he excommunicated <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and expoſed his kingdome for a prey to the firſt that could get it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19944:26"/> hee ordayned an army by Sea into <hi>Sicilie</hi> againſt <hi>Charles;</hi> and abſolued his ſubiects of their oath. Note that all the paſtime of Popes, is, to ſet Princes together by the eares. Hee granted to <hi>Rome</hi> the choyce of two Senators, of the Nobilitie, and excommunicated <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liolagus</hi> Emperour of <hi>Greece.</hi> He tooke the Cencubine of his predeceſſour <hi>Nicholas:</hi> but leſt ſuch an accident might happen him as did vnto others; namely, that if he had a childe, it ſhould be like vnto a Beare, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the Beares which had beene paynted in the Pallace by a Pope of the houſe of the <hi>Vrſins,</hi> ſhould be defaced: For he knew well, that the figure of things vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which women thinke, when they conceiue, oft-times, is certainely imprinted in them. <hi>The. Cooper Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chron.</hi> But as once hee was taking his ordinary refection with his Captaines, he was taken with a ſecret mallady whereof he died. See <hi>Cuſalanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Honorius</hi> the fourth ſate two yeeres: he excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>Peter</hi> King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> who then occupied the kingdome of <hi>Sicilie</hi> againſt <hi>Charles,</hi> and confirmed the Edict of his Predeceſſour againſt him. Thus they ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed one another in cruelty: he confirmed the Sect of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> He died. 1288.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fourth ſate foure yeeres, and one month. <hi>Naucler.</hi> Some ſay ſix yeeres. Many cruell warres, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, diſſentions, and brawles in his time happened in <hi>Rome,</hi> vpon his occaſion, giuing more countenance to the one part, then to the other: and this continued two yeeres. <hi>Faſci<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> temporum. Nicholas</hi> died of griefe, becauſe all things happened not after his wiſh. 1291.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19944:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the fift ſate two yeeres and fiue moneths: he went about the reformation of the Clergie: they grind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their teeth at him, called him Sot and Dotard: one of theſe companions killed <hi>Benet;</hi> ſuborned another, who making a cranny in his chamber, many nights cryed as it had beene an Angell from heauen, <hi>Geleſtine, Geleſtine,</hi> renounce thy Papacy, for that charge exceedeth thy force. Some alſo in the day time counſelled him to giue ouer his Popedome, and prouide for his ſaluation. Note wee here that <hi>Rome</hi> cannot abide to heare of reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As he returned from <hi>Naples,</hi> he diſmiſſed himſelfe of that charge, &amp;c. See <hi>Chriſtian Maſsius:</hi> yet firſt hee made a conſtitution by all their conſents, That it ſhould be lawfull for a Pope to giue ouer ſuch a charge: which <hi>Boniface</hi> his ſucceſſour ſubtilly confirmed, and placed it in the ſixt booke of his Decretalls: But this <hi>Boniface</hi> fearing that the people deſpiſing him, ſhould cleaue vnto <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> cauſed him to be put in cloſe priſon, where he dyed. 1295.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight ſate eight yeeres and nine moneths: He obtained the place (as before) by fraud and violence, to his predeceſſour <hi>Celeſtine.</hi> This is he of whom it is ſpoken, that hee entred as a Foxe, reigned as a Lion, and died as a Dogge. He was a terrour to Emperours, Kings and Princes, Nations and People, which he more reſpected then Religion, which gaue and tooke away kingdomes at his pleaſure, extraordinarily thirſting af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gold from all places. He was alſo cruell againſt the dead, for he cauſed a godly man, buried twenty yeeres before, to be taken out of his graue, and burnt for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as he decreed. His pride and arrogancie was ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19944:27"/> to Princes, as <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> to bring vnder his pride made forces againſt him, inuaded him priuily in the night at <hi>Anagni,</hi> and breaking downe the gates, tooke him in his fathers houſe, and carried him to <hi>Rome</hi> priſoner, where through griefe of minde he died, thirtie fiue dayes after, and all his goods and treaſure went to pillage. <hi>Platin. Iohn de la Maire.</hi> On Aſhwedneſday he gaue Aſhes vnto the people of <hi>Genes:</hi> and <hi>Porchat</hi> the Archbiſhop of the Towne preſented himſelfe before him, and vnderſtanding that hee was of the <hi>Gebellins,</hi> whom he hated, hee being on his knees vncouered, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting neither day nor place, people, or religion, in his malice he caſt an handfull of aſhes in his eies, &amp; abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Scripture ſaid: <hi>Remember that thou art a Gebelline, and that with Gebelius thou ſhalt be brought to aſhes:</hi> and ſtrait depriued the Archbiſhop of his dignity, though after he reſtored him. <hi>Platina. Criniſ. Cor. Abb.</hi> 1295.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the eleuenth ſate eight moneths: hee was a good man, and ſtudied for concord: hee contemned Friers, reuoked <hi>Bonifaces</hi> Decrees. Comming to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſe,</hi> he there fell ſicke, and dyed: But it was after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that a certaine <hi>Abbeſſe</hi> preſented vnto him poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned figges, whereof hee dyed; and <hi>Leander</hi> affirmeth hee dyed of poyſon. 1304.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the fift ſate at <hi>Auignon</hi> eight yeeres and tenne moneths: hee was enthronized at <hi>Lyons,</hi> in the Church of Saint <hi>Iuſt,</hi> with a mighty concourſe of the Cleargie, and all eſtates. But their great pompe was mixed with great mourning: for as an innumerable multitude were mounted vpon an olde wall of Saint <hi>Iuſt,</hi> the ſayd wall fell, and ſlew Duke <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Brittaine:</hi> The King was
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19944:27"/> there wounded, and the Pope throwne ouer his horſe, and troden vnder foote, where he loſt a rich Carbuncle out of his triple Crowne, eſteemed at ſixe thouſand florens of golde, (<hi>Pride muſt haue a fall:</hi>) beſides, more then twelue other noble perſons were there wounded, and dyed. Theſe things done, the King departed, and the Pope made his reſidencie at <hi>Auignon.</hi> This Pope kept his <hi>Roman</hi> Court, not at <hi>Rome,</hi> but at <hi>Auignon,</hi> where it abode by the ſpace of ſeauentie three yeeres, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it returned to <hi>Rome.</hi> See <hi>Iohn le Maire.</hi> Hee ſent three Cardinalls to gouerne <hi>Rome.</hi> This <hi>Clement</hi> was a publique whoore-monger, and a great maintayner of harlots. <hi>Chron. Herm. Paralip. Veſp.</hi> He gaue to them that offered themſelues againſt the <hi>Turke,</hi> foure ſoules out of Purgatory, at their will, <hi>Agrippa de vanitat.</hi> This Pope commanded the Angells to carry into the ioyes of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radice, and draw out of Purgatory, the ſoule of him whoſoeuer ſhould die in the way going in pilgrimage to <hi>Rome:</hi> moreouer, that the paines of hell ſhall no way be inflicted vpon them. In a Bull which is kept by Coppy at <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Limego</hi> at this day. <hi>Agrippa de vanit. Scient.</hi> Hee condemned them that would not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the bread of the Euchariſt. He ordained, That the oathes deliuered to Princes, were not oathes of ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, but of fidelity. Hee ordayned a feaſt inſtituted in the honour of the bread in the Euchariſt, which the Papiſts call Gods feaſt. Hee pronounced that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Saints ought to be greatly honoured. Finally, he being tormented with a fluxe of the belly, and paine of the ſtomacke and ſides, he deceaſed in a Caſtle called <hi>Rocquemaure</hi> vpon <hi>Boſue</hi> 1314.</p>
               <p>Behold here how humane traditions doe increaſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19944:28"/> of the word of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the three and twentith ſate nineteene yeeres and foure moneths. Hee condemned the Conſtitutions of <hi>Nicholas. Deer. 6. tit.</hi> 12. He made a Conſtitution againſt Friers Minors: he taught certaine errours, amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that ſoules ſo ſoone as they were diſpoyled of the bodies, ſhould not ſee God before the laſt Iudgement. <hi>Maſsius</hi> witneſſeth, his father had ſo taught him before. He writ to the <hi>Grecians,</hi> that there was but one Church, whereof hee was chiefe, and the Vicar of Ieſus Chriſt. The <hi>Grecians</hi> anſwered, Wee beleeue ſurely that thy power is very great ouer thy ſubiects; we cannot indure thy extreame pride, nor ſatisfie thy couetouſneſſe: the Diuell be with thee, for God is with vs. <hi>Iohn de la Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauill</hi> in his ſixt booke rehearſeth it. He declared <hi>Lewes de Bauiere</hi> a Rebell, Schiſmaticke, and Heretike, becauſe (being choſen Emperour) hee tooke the gouernement without any oath to the Pope of ſubiection. <hi>Hiero Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</hi> The Emperour came to appeaſe the Popes rage to <hi>Millaine,</hi> and ſent to <hi>Auignon,</hi> to the Pope, that hee would grant him kindly, the ornaments of the Empire, the Pope refuſed his Ambaſſadours, with great ſhame, and cited the Emperour peremptorily, that hee would come to <hi>Auignon,</hi> and ſubmit himſelfe to the ordinances of the Church. The Emperour knowing their tyranny, would not ſubmit himſelfe; as if hee were his ſeruant, and would not goe, but ſent againe to make the ſame requeſt. The Pope perſiſted in his opinion, &amp;c. The Emperour calling vnto him many Princes and Lords of <hi>Italie,</hi> came to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was honourably receiued of the people. The greateſt Lords of <hi>Rome</hi> ſent Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours to the Pope, beſeeching him to viſit the towne,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19944:28"/> and grant to the King of the <hi>Romans</hi> the imperiall orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: which if he refuſed to doe, they proteſted to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the auncient Law, and to vſe the right of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> people. The Pope hearing the Embaſſage, draue them backe ſhamefully with vile words, and threates; which the <hi>Roman</hi> people ſeeing, departed, and ſo by the commandement of all the Clergie, and people, hee was crowned, &amp;c. Hereupon the Pope accuſed him as one guiltie of diuine treaſon, and an heretike, and publiſhed againſt him a very rigorous Proceſſe. (Oh Luciferian pride, vnbeſeeming <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour.) The Emperour fortifying himſelfe, publiſhed in all parts of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, an appellation againſt the Pope, that hee for his part doth execute the Teſtament of Ieſus Chriſt, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing peace; which the Pope diſturbeth in all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and remembers not, that all the honour he now hath, was graunted by Saint <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to <hi>Silueſter,</hi> when he was yet hid, and therefore accuſeth him of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude, &amp;c. and then they agreed to bring into the Church of Chriſt, the auncient cuſtome obſerued in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the Pope; namely, that being choſen by the people, he ſhould be confirmed by the Emperour: and therefore one, called <hi>Peter Carbaria,</hi> a Frier, was created Pope, and called <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fift: and Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> was declared an hereticke, a tyrant of the Church, and not a Paſtour, but a perturber of the peace of Chriſtians: which proceedings the Emperour and the Princes, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant at the Counſell held at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſubmitted to the iudgement of the Catholique Church. <hi>Marius.</hi> This done, the Emperour returned into <hi>Almaine,</hi> and Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> remayned in <hi>Italy.</hi> But finally <hi>Boniface,</hi> County of <hi>Piſe,</hi> deliuered him to Pope <hi>Iohn,</hi> and he died in great
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19944:29"/> miſery, being ſtraitly detained. See <hi>Suppl. Chron. Platin.</hi> 1334.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benet</hi> the twelfth ſate ſeuen yeeres and three months: hee was enemy to the Emperour <hi>Lewis,</hi> as his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour; for he renewed the excommunication, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyled him of all honour. <hi>Marius. Lewis</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Frankford</hi> all the Electors, &amp;c. He ſhewed, that it onely pertaineth to the Electors of the Empire, and not to any other, to chooſe the King of <hi>Romans,</hi> or Emperour, for in ſubſtance they are all one: which Emperour may exerciſe the affaires of the Empire, without any confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the <hi>Roman</hi> ſeate: Who ought to be ſacred by the Pope, after notice by the Princes, that he is legit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately choſen: But if the Pope refuſe, hee may be proclaymed Emperour <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> by any Catholique Biſhop whatſoeuer, as hath beene long time vſed: and all ſuch Vnctions are onely certayne ceremonies, inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Popes, which giue only the name, not the thing. The Emperour makes not an oathe of fidelitie to the Popes, but for the defence of the Faith; not to giue him any ſuperioritie in things which concerne the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raltie. Further, hee ſhewed in the vacancie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, it is falſe, that the right is deuolued vnto the Pope, and that this is againſt the liberty and dignity of the Empire: but that by a cuſtome approued, and vſed of long time, without any contradiction, during the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Empire, it pertaineth to the Countie <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> of <hi>Rheine,</hi> to haue the managing of the affaires of the Empire. This done, he yeelded a reaſon of his faith, and purged himſelfe of all things obiected againſt him, by <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Benet</hi> the twelfth.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19944:29"/>
               <p>The integrity of this <hi>Lewis</hi> ſo preuayled with Pope <hi>Bennet,</hi> as a peace was after concluded betweene them; inſomuch as the French Ambaſſadours called the Pope, the Protector of Heretickes. <hi>Bennet</hi> abſolued him of his excommunication; but being menaced by the King of <hi>France,</hi> hee left the Sentence giuen by his predeceſſour againſt <hi>Lewis.</hi> This Pope was an olde adulterer, and bought deare the Siſter of <hi>Francis Petrarke</hi> a faire wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, of her brother called <hi>Gerard.</hi> He contradicted his predeceſſours hereſie, affirming, that the ſoules of the godly, as ſoone as they be departed from the body, do ſee the face of God. <hi>Decret. Benedictus Deus in donis.</hi> He ſaid the Pope had no parents. <hi>Faſci Temporum.</hi> He dyed at <hi>Auignon,</hi> to the great ioy of many. <hi>Oppoſition. Andrew de Caſtra. &amp; Bardoſanes.</hi> He defended Grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Free-will. <hi>Iohn de Rupe Sciſſa</hi> taught, the Pope to be Antechriſt, and the Church of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the ſixt ſate eleuen yeeres in <hi>Auignon:</hi> he was a man very deſirous of women, of honour and power: Led with a diabolicall furie, hee fixed letters vpon the gates and doores of Temples, by which he threatned the Emperour vpon grieuous puniſhment, that within three dayes he ſhould renounce the right of the Empire. <hi>H. Marius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Emperour came to <hi>Frankeford,</hi> and ſought the Popes fauour. The Pope anſwered the Ambaſſadours, that he neuer would pardon <hi>Lewis,</hi> but vpon very vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and cruell conditions, and ſo gaue a formulary to the Ambaſſadours. <hi>Lewis</hi> ſhewed this to the Princes, &amp;c. The Princes iudged them to tend to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Empire, and promiſed ayde: but the Pope
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19944:30"/> moſt cruelly excommunicated <hi>Lewis.</hi> Hee depriued <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Magunce,</hi> one of the Electours, and ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Electors to chooſe a new Emperour: they choſe <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth, who was crowned in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the emperie of <hi>Lewis;</hi> but he was not reputed Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, no not after the death of <hi>Lewis. Lewis</hi> was poyſoned, as is ſayd, hauing drunke of the cup of <hi>Iane</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Auſtrich;</hi> at the poynt of death he cryed: <hi>O God be mercifull to mee a poore ſinner. Munster,</hi> and others. 1348. The Pope died ſodainely, being ſtrucken with an impoſtume. 1353.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oppoſition. Conrad Hagar</hi> taught, that the Sacrament of the Maſſe was auaileable neither for quicke nor dead. <hi>Francis Patriarcha</hi> condemned Monkes and Friers, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Rome</hi> the whoore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Schoole of Errour, the Temple of Hereſie. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 20. with many others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſixt ſate nine yeeres: He would haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered a Tenth of the Clergie, but was denyed, and ſo ceaſed. He was ſparing in his diet, and liuing; but in expences of warre, very large. This Pope ordayned the feaſt of Ieſus Chriſts Launce and Nailes: to the end thoſe dead Idols might be adored by the Chriſtians. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death was ſuch an Eclipſe of the Sunne as was neuer ſeene. <hi>Maſsius. Plat.</hi> As he was preparing an army by Sea againſt the Turke, the <hi>Romans</hi> being in troubles and ſeditions, he was ſo vexed in minde, that hee dyed with griefe. <hi>Anno</hi> 1362.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrban</hi> the fift ſate eight yeeres: He ſent a Legat into <hi>Italie,</hi> with full power, and ſo repreſſed the Vicounts, and other Gouernours of Townes; threatning great loſſes, if they would not ſubmit themſelues vnder the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19944:30"/> obedience of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. <hi>Armacan</hi> a learned man and Biſhop of <hi>Ireland,</hi> publiſhed Concluſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Friers, teaching that it was a villainous thing for a Chriſtian to begge without neede. <hi>Volater.</hi> He ſayd he could not finde foure Bibles in <hi>Oxford.</hi> Ieſuites began by <hi>Iohn Columbau,</hi> and <hi>Francis Vincent</hi> of <hi>Burgony. Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. Sabell. Iohn Wickecliffe</hi> of <hi>Oxford</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> a rare Theologian, he touched liuely the abuſes of the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, againſt begging Friers and Monkes; hee had King <hi>Edward</hi> to friend. The Pope as he returned into <hi>France</hi> dyed at <hi>Marcellus,</hi> not without ſuſpition of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Sabell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the fift Emperour and King of <hi>France,</hi> cauſed the Scripture to be tranſlated into French. 1366.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the eleuenth ſate at <hi>Auignon</hi> ſeauen yeeres and fiue moneths: Many of the townes of <hi>Italy</hi> reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his obedience: At the perſwaſion of a Nunne, he pronounced ſentence of Interdiction againſt the <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentines</hi> the firſt Authors, and ſeiſed all the townes about them, and made warre vpon them. <hi>Naucler. Gregorie</hi> dyed, being tormented with an intollerable paine in the bladder. <hi>Plat.</hi> 1378.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſixt ſate eleuen yeeres: he was a cruell man, of whom by prayer nothing could be obtayned. <hi>Craut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zius.</hi> He being come to the Popedome, ſought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge himſelfe: he was forſaken of his Cardinalls, as a falſe Pope, and <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeauenth choſen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeauenth ſate in <hi>Auignon</hi> fifteene yeeres: and thus beganne the two and twentith Schiſme of two Popes 29. yeeres, vntill the Counſell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19944:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> one curſing and warring with the other, that about 200000. were miſerably ſlaine and drowned. <hi>Clement</hi> was choſen three months after <hi>Vrban. Vrban</hi> made thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie new Cardinals in one day, and diſplaced the old, and put them in priſon. Hee was vnder the ſafe keeping of the King of <hi>Naples,</hi> for his pride certayne dayes; at the length, deſiring that hee might goe to new <hi>Ceſarea</hi> for his health, hee was ſet at libertie, where hee gathered forces againſt the King: But <hi>Raymundus</hi> the Generall of the Kings forces, <hi>Vrban</hi> comming with all his Court to the next ſhore, he ſhipped them, and brought the Pope to <hi>Genua,</hi> and of ſeauen Cardinals being taken at new <hi>Ceſarea,</hi> putting fiue of them into ſackes, he drowned them in the Sea, becauſe he thought they fauoured <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> The Pope <hi>Vrban</hi> ſucceeding vnhappily in his Popedome, dyed the eleuenth yeere of his Popedome, few lamenting his death, as a rude and execrable perſon. <hi>Plattina. Theodor. Cerinth.</hi> The waters and fountaines were poyſoned, whereof he dyed, and all his nobility. <hi>Naucler.</hi> Theſe two Popes ſent terrible Bulls into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers parts of the world, and ſo ſowed defamatorie bookes, wherein they named one another Antechriſt, Schiſmatickes. Heretickes, tyrants, traytors, theeues, vniuſt, ſowers of tares, and children of <hi>Belial. Iohn de Ligni,</hi> in a Treatiſe in fauour of <hi>Vrban,</hi> and the Abbot of Saint <hi>Vaſt:</hi> the Kings Chancellor of <hi>France,</hi> in fauour of <hi>Clement; That the Pope is Antechriſt,</hi> no better witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes then themſelues. <hi>Clement</hi> dyed at <hi>Auignon 1394. Matthias</hi> a <hi>Bohemian</hi> proueth the Pope to be Antechriſt, and Friers, heretickes. <hi>Walter Brut:</hi> In likewiſe, many Noble men in <hi>England</hi> maintained <hi>Wickecliffes</hi> doctrine; The Lord <hi>Montague,</hi> Lord <hi>Clifford,</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisburie.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19944:31"/> Swinderby</hi> a prieſt wrote againſt Tranſubſtantiation. 1387.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth ſate at <hi>Rome</hi> fifteene yeeres. Hee was choſen after <hi>Vrban.</hi> He made a Law whereby hee obtayned the ſeigniorie of all the world, that is, that no Parſon ſhould be promoted to any Benefice, before hee had payed to the Apoſtolique Chamber, all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes of the firſt yeere. Hee made great marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize of Indulgences, and ſold them for money.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bennet</hi> the thirteenth ſate at <hi>Auignon</hi> one and twentie yeeres: He gaue to <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixt, King of <hi>France,</hi> the tenth part of all Eccleſiaſticall goods, to make him his friend, and to diuide the ſpoyle. And as hee was in his Country, <hi>Catalongue,</hi> in a ſtrong Caſtle called <hi>Pauiſcole,</hi> maintaining himſelfe the true Vicar of Ieſus Chriſt, hee was condemned many wayes by the authority of the ſayd Counſell. Finally, dying at <hi>Pauiſcole,</hi> he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Cardinals, that preſently they ſhould chooſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in his place, and they elected one <hi>Giles Menios,</hi> and called him <hi>Clement</hi> the eight. <hi>Plattina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Pope made Cardinalls at the inſtigation of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> King, and did all that a Pope ſhould doe. But after <hi>Martin</hi> 1. had agreed with <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement <hi>Giles</hi> renounced all his right to the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and was declared Biſhop of <hi>Maiorque;</hi> and the Cardinalls made by him willingly renounced their dignities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſeauenth was choſen after <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth ſate at <hi>Rome</hi> two yeeres: he being Cardinall, was wont to taxe the negligence and fearefulneſſe of the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19944:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> former Popes: for he ſaid, it came to paſſe through their ſloath, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the deſtruction of the whole Chriſtian Common-wealth, was not yet cut off. But when he came to the Papacie, he followed the ſteppes of <hi>Vrban,</hi> and <hi>Boniface,</hi> whom being a priuate man, hee had taxed. Hee warred with the Citizens of <hi>Rome.</hi> The Anti-pope <hi>Benedict</hi> reclayming. <hi>Plattina.</hi> With the neglect of his ſepulcher his memory periſhed. Hee had a care that <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fift ſhould be reſtored to his Popedome. <hi>Plat.</hi> 1404.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the twelfth ſate eight yeeres: he was choſen after the death of <hi>Innocent,</hi> and an oath taken to yeeld, if the profit of the Church required it, but hee would not, though hee promiſed before a Notarie, before he was confirmed Pope, 1407. <hi>Benet,</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> were perſwaded by <hi>Charles</hi> the ſixt Emperour, for the good and vnion of the Church, to giue ouer their rights. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> gaue no anſwere: but diſmiſſed the Ambaſſadour without farewell; and for feare to be conſtrained, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided for himſelfe. A Counſell was held at <hi>Pice,</hi> to v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the vniuerſall Church, whereunto <hi>Gregorie</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> were cited, but had no care to appeare, but derided it. So at the ſaid Counſell, <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Benet</hi> were both depoſed, &amp; one called <hi>Alexander</hi> was inſtituted; ſo were three Popes together: but <hi>Gregorie</hi> fled to <hi>Austrich, &amp;c.</hi> To their depoſition all Chriſtian Nations conſented, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a part of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the Count <hi>Arnimacke,</hi> and the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> who fauoured <hi>Benet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the fift ſate eight moneths. He was a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, a worthy and a godly man: hee was choſen with the conſent of all the Cardinalls in the Counſell of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19944:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Pice.</hi> Thus <hi>Gregorie</hi> and <hi>Bennet</hi> not giuing ouer, were three Popes at once. <hi>Alexander</hi> was ſo liberall to the poore, and to men worthy of his charity, as within a while he left nothing to himſelfe. Whereupon, in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, he was wont to ſay: He had been a rich Biſhop, a poore Cardinal, and a beggerly Pope. After the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Pice,</hi> he goeth to <hi>Bononie,</hi> where he fell grieuouſly ſicke; and knowing Death to be neere, the Cardinalls comming vnto him, he exhorted them to concord and peace, and to preſerue the dignity of the Church, and teſtified, though Death were before his eyes, yet he did not feare, &amp;c. And when hee could hardly vtter the words, hee ſayd, <hi>My peace I giue vnto you, my peace I leaue with you.</hi> See <hi>Plat.</hi> 1409.</p>
               <p>It is thought he had a poiſoned drinke giuen him of a Phyſitian, <hi>Marcellus</hi> of <hi>Parma,</hi> hired by <hi>Balthazar</hi> a Cardinall (whom hee fauoured) with a great ſumme of money. <hi>Panecius</hi> reciteth in his 56. Sermon, and <hi>Eſtate of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note, <hi>Rome</hi> cannot abide an honeſt man to be Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty foure ſucceeded <hi>Alexander,</hi> before <hi>Balthazer Coſſe,</hi> Cardinall: hee ſate fiue yeeres at <hi>Bolog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie;</hi> he came to the Popedome, rather by force and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then by free Canonicall Election: For being at <hi>Bolognie,</hi> rather as a Lord and Maſter then a Legate, the Fathers being aſſembled to chooſe a Pope, hee excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly threatned them, if they elected not ſuch a one as pleaſed him: Therefore many were preſented; but hee approued none. Then ſayd the Cardinalls vnto him, Name him whom you like. Then hee anſwered, Giue me Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Mantle, and pontificall habite, and I
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19944:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> will giue them to him, whom I would haue to be Pope. When hee had receiued them, hee put them vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſayd; It is I that am Pope: and though they were not pleaſed therewith, yet they were faine to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble; ſo furious terrible, and inuironed with ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers was he. This reporteth <hi>Stella.</hi> After his Election he went to <hi>Rome</hi> to hold a Synode. In the firſt Seſſion, the Pope ſitting on a high ſeate, &amp;c. there came an Owle, and ſate vpon one of the balkes of the Temple, looking directly vpon the Pope, ſaluting him with a fearefull ſong: The company could ſcarſe keepe themſelues from laughing. The Pope beganne to be aſhamed, to ſweat, and to be tormented in himſelfe; and finally, finding no way to eaſe himſelfe, he diſmiſſed the company, and retired. There was another Seſſion after this, wherein came the like; but this Owle could not be chaſed away, neither with cries, nor ſtones, nor for ſtaues that were throwne at him. <hi>Nicholas Clemengis</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Baieux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Counſel of <hi>Conſtance</hi> aſſembled, where the Pope appeared. 1414. This Counſell indured foure yeeres; ſixe of <hi>Gregories</hi> Cardinalls approued the Counſell. <hi>Naucler. Iohn Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hierome of Prage</hi> were ſent for, and had the Emperours ſafe-conduct: and becauſe they would not recant, they were notwithſtanding both burnt. Many crimes were obiected againſt the Pope; whereupon he fled away in a diſguiſed habite; and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed many places for his defence. <hi>Naucler.</hi> He was taken, and brought to <hi>Constance,</hi> and there detained in priſon: After they proued againſt him fiftie and foure criminall Articles. He was depoſed by all the Counſell. Himſelfe approued his depoſitions, &amp;c. <hi>Naucler.</hi> 1416. They
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19944:33"/> cited alſo <hi>Gregorie</hi> the twelfth, but he reſigned his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie into the hands of the Counſell. Hee was created Legate in the Marqueſdome of <hi>Ancon:</hi> where hee dyed ſoone after. <hi>Iohn de la Maire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martine</hi> the fifth (though <hi>Benets</hi> Cardinalls chooſe <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, but preuayled not) was choſen of thirty three Cardinalls in the Counſell of <hi>Constance,</hi> he ſate foureteene yeeres. Hee condemned all the acts of the former Popes in the Schiſme. <hi>Iohn</hi> being deliuered out of priſon commeth to <hi>Florence</hi> vnto <hi>Martine,</hi> kiſſed his feet, and acknowledged him true Pope, and Chriſts Vicar. <hi>Martine</hi> receiuing him into the number of the Cardinalls, created him Biſhop of <hi>Tuſculane:</hi> but he (as it is thought) not induring a priuate life, through griefe of minde, after certaine moneths, dyed. <hi>Martine</hi> of a Biſhop of <hi>Florence,</hi> created an Archbiſhop. The yeere after, the Riuer <hi>Tibris</hi> did ſo increaſe as it drowned all the plaines in <hi>Rome,</hi> and filled the Temple <hi>Pantheon,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the high Altar. A great plague enſued, that compelled them to change the place and time of the Counſell intended. Certaine Cardinalls, after the death of <hi>Iohn</hi> the foure and twentieth, created a new Pope, and called him <hi>Clement</hi> the eight: but after a while hee gaue ouer, the reſt were put in priſon. Pope <hi>Martine</hi> died of an Apoplexie. 1431.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth ſate ſixeteene yeeres: after his creation, hee appoynted a certayne day for a generall Conſiſtorie; whither came ſo great a multitude, that the beames of the place cracking, it bred ſuch a feare, that in the flying away of the people, the Biſhop of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagal,</hi> a Citizen of <hi>Rome</hi> was boren downe, and dyed.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19944:34"/> The Popes pride prouoked much warres in the Citty, and abroad, and he was often driuen to his ſtraits, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſt with warres euery way. The Emperour and other Princes and Prelates, admoniſhed him twice or thrice, to appoynt a conuenient place at <hi>Baſill</hi> for the Counſell, which was concluded in the Counſell of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> from tenne yeeres to tenne yeeres, and to come thither with his Cardinals: otherwiſe they would deale with him as with an enemie, and an obſtinate perſon. Whereunto hee aſſented; But hee was ſo vexed with warres on euery ſide, as hee had ſcarſe libertie to reſt. But hee confirmed the Counſell of <hi>Baſill,</hi> begunne by <hi>Martine</hi> his predeceſſour; and hee was by the ſame depoſed, and condemned an Hereticke, and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke. <hi>Plat.</hi> The Counſell of <hi>Baſill</hi> choſe <hi>Faelix.</hi> 1448.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Faelix</hi> the fift Duke of <hi>Sauore,</hi> was choſen by the Counſell of <hi>Baſill,</hi> Anti-pape; but <hi>Eugenius</hi> depoſed, and would not yeeld; ſo there was a Schiſme of two Popes thirteene yeeres: ſome ſay ſixeteene together, till <hi>Faelix</hi> was contented to giue ouer to <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fift. <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin.</hi> 1439. Some followed <hi>Eugenius,</hi> ſome <hi>Faelix,</hi> ſome Newtrails, and obeyed neither. <hi>Platt.</hi> Who was then Chriſts Vicar?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fift ſate at <hi>Rome</hi> eight yeeres: Hee was crowned the nineteenth of March 1447. yet ceaſed not the Schiſme of two Popes: for <hi>Faelix</hi> counted himſelfe ſtill Pope. In the yeere 1448. <hi>Faelix</hi> renounced the Popedome, and <hi>Nicholas</hi> reigned alone. <hi>Nicholas</hi> held a Iubilie at <hi>Rome,</hi> 1450. whither reſorted ſuch a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of people, as many were ſtifled as they entred and came out of the Churches: There periſhed about two
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19944:34"/> hundred perſons, beſides a number which fell into the floud as they paſſed ouer the bridge of Saint <hi>Angelo.</hi> This Pope died of a feauer and gout. <hi>Naucler. Plattina.</hi> Others ſay hee was poyſoned, as appeared by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes, opened. <hi>Sea of Hiſtories.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Calixt</hi> the third, ſate three yeeres: he ſtirred vp Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians againſt the <hi>Turke;</hi> he ordayned, that no perſon ſhould appeale from the Pope to the Counſell. He ſold letters of pardons for fiue ducats a peece, ſaith <hi>Valerius,</hi> whereby he left vnto his ſucceſſours, an hundred and fifteene thouſand Ducats; he died in Iuly. 1458.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pius</hi> the ſecond ſate ſixe yeeres: hee was very ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: hee publiſhed a voyage againſt the <hi>Turke;</hi> vnder colour of warring againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> the Popes gat great ſtore of ſiluer. Hee exceeded in crueltie: before hee was Pope, hee had written with ſingular diligence, two bookes of the Acts of the Counſell of <hi>Baſill:</hi> but being Pope, he ſought to repreſſe them, labouring, not to leſſen the Papall tyranny, but to increaſe it in what he could. <hi>Stella.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He made warres with <hi>Borge</hi> Duke of <hi>Mutine,</hi> becauſe he fauoured <hi>Sigiſmund Malateſt,</hi> with many other great cruelties. For his profit he depoſed many Biſhops: He was ſumptuous in building: hee made a Sepulchre of Marble for his fathers and mothers bones. See <hi>Plattina.</hi> Amongſt many things left in writing, this was one: With great reaſon (ſaith he) was Marriage taken from Prieſts; yet there is a farre greater reaſon, wherefore it ought to haue beene yeelded them againe. Alſo in his ſecond booke of Counſells he ſaith: It may be that it were not the worſe if a many Prieſts were married: for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19944:35"/> many being married Prieſts ſhould be ſaued; which in their barren ſingleneſſe are damned. Himſelfe aboliſhed the Monaſteries of S. <hi>Brigit,</hi> and S. <hi>Clare,</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them out, that they might burne no more, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the habite of Religion, they ſhould not hide whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Caelius ſecundus.</hi> Hee was ſurprized of a ſlowe feauer, whereof hee died at <hi>Ancon. 1464. Plattina. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond ſate ſeauen yeeres: he was of a proude ſpirit, ambitious, and couetous. Hee exceeded all his anceſtors in ſumptuous attire, and all kinde of precious attire. <hi>Plattina.</hi> O noble Succeſſour of <hi>Peter!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee was an enemy to learning: hee put away many learned men, as forreiners, and ſtrangers, with their bookes giuen to the ſpoyle: But diuers, with <hi>Plattina</hi> himſelfe, deſiring the matter might be referred vnto the Iudges, the Pope in great anger anſwered: Do you not know, that all Iudgement is placed in our breaſt? <hi>Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi> wrote a letter to the Pope, deſiring, that if without cauſe he would ſpoyle them of their iuſt purchaſe, yet it would pleaſe him, they might haue leaue to complaine of their wrong, and vniuſt ignominy: For being bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of you, wee muſt paſſe vnto Kings and Princes; and we will intreate them that you appoint a Counſell, wherein you may be conſtrained to giue a reaſon of your doing. <hi>Paulus</hi> hauing read the letter, he preſently chargeth me of Libells ſpreading out againſt him. And though I freed my ſelfe of that charge, becauſe I had ſet my name thereto: yet I was bound with grieuous fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and put into a high Tower, in the middeſt of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, expoſed to all windes, foure months. At the length,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19944:35"/> at the importunate ſuite of a Cardinall, I was ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie; with admonition, that I ſhould not depart the Citie, affirming, that if I went among the Indies, <hi>Paul</hi> would fetch me thence. He was ſodainely put in feare by a report that youths, hauing <hi>Calimacho</hi> their Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, had conſpired againſt him, whereby he feared to be ſurprized at home, and abroad; whereupon hee put many to torture, with Captaine <hi>Calimacho,</hi> whereof many died in the torture. Hee was a great eater of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons; he eate the ſame day that he died, in the night, two very great Melons: he died of an Apoplexie, the tenth of the Kalends of Auguſt. 1471. being alone in his Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, no man ſeeing him; when that day being very mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hee had a Conſiſtory: He went about to eſtabliſh Prieſts marriages, but hee was preuented by death. It was ſaid, when hee came abroad, he was wont to paint his face, with all kinde of precious ſtones about him, <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi>-like, deſirous to be ſeene and wondered at. Hee was a great drinker, but of ſmall wines. He ſo hated the ſtudy of humanitie, as he called the ſtudents thereof by one name, Heretickes. Hereupon he perſwaded the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> they ſhould no longer bring vp their children in learning, it was enough if they learned to reade and write <hi>Plattin.</hi> Others ſay, the Diuell brake his necke, as he was committing Sodomatrie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth ſate thirteen yeeres: he was in great danger of his life at his Coronation, by reaſon of a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, whileſt they carried him in his Litter to the Church of <hi>Lateran:</hi> hee was in danger of his life, being aſſailed with ſtones, ſo as he was forſaken almoſt of all that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied his Litter. Hee made many warres againſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19944:36"/> 
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Pouill.</hi> Hee builded in <hi>Rome</hi> Stewes for both kindes. <hi>Cornelius Agrippa. cap.</hi> 64. he graunted to Cardinalls the vſe of Sodomatry, for three hot mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths. <hi>Sextus</hi> being ſicke of a feuer, vnderſtanding that a peace was made betwixt the <hi>Venetians</hi> and other Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates, ſodainely yeelded the ſpirit. <hi>Naucler.</hi> The rents of the Curtizans amounted to the value of twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ducats yeerely. <hi>Onuphrius. Agrippa de vanit. Scient. Wiſellus de Indulgentijs.</hi> Witneſſes. <hi>Naucler.</hi> 1484.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocens</hi> the eight ſate eight yeeres: hee was once a poore childe, he was nouriſhed amongeſt the ſeruants of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of <hi>Sicilie:</hi> afterward he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> he remained long time with <hi>Philip</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Bolongne.</hi> After hee was made Biſhop of <hi>Sauonne,</hi> at the length he was made Cardinall, and Pope. He was of a great ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but farre from learning. Almoſt from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his Popedome, hee conſpired againſt <hi>Ferdinand</hi> (that brought him vp) with the Princes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and warred againſt him, &amp;c. but being wearied with warres, he gaue himſelfe to all pleaſures. He aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his baſtards, as <hi>Francis,</hi> and inriched his daughter, <hi>Theodorin,</hi> which he married to a rich man of <hi>Genoa.</hi> He begat eight ſons and as many daughters. <hi>Marcellus poeta.</hi> No maruell though <hi>Rome</hi> calles him Father. See his Epitaph following:
<q>
                     <l>Why ſeekeſt thou witnes to proue <hi>Cibo</hi> a man?</l>
                     <l>Looke on his brats, faire gages, deny't and you can:</l>
                     <l>Eight bastard ſonnes he begat, as many daughters,</l>
                     <l>Worthily then may <hi>Rome</hi> count this man <hi>Father,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <bibl>ſaith <hi>Marcellus.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Alluding to the triall of the Sexe, ordayned after the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19944:36"/> deceit of Pope <hi>Ioane:</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>Vncleanneſſe, Auarice, Sloath, Gluttony,</l>
                     <l>Are heere octaue, intomb'd, where thou doſt lye.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, called <hi>Borgia,</hi> before a Cardinall: ſeeking to mount higher, being a Negromancer; hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the helpe of the Diuell, who promiſed him vpon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement by oath, and writing, ſo as hee would in all things thew himſelfe a faithfull protectour of Sathan. Afterward the Diuell came vnto him (hauing promiſed he ſhould not appeare in any hideous or fearfull forme) honourably apparrelled, who after certaine talke had betwixt them, aſſured the Cardinall he ſhould be Pope. <hi>Borgia</hi> being very ioyous, hee inquired how long hee ſhould reigne: The Diuell gaue him an ambiguous an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> that hee ſhould reigne, the ſpace of eleauen and eight. The Cardinall fooliſhly promiſed himſelfe nineteene yeeres; but Sathan meant eleuen yeeres and eight moneths. Now being choſen Pope, hee named himſelfe <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt: he made his baſtard ſonne called <hi>Valentine,</hi> being a Cardinall, a Duke, and ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him <hi>Caeſar Borgia:</hi> he ſhed much bloud, ſaith <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerius.</hi> He gathered ſiluer as much as hee could, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie his luſt. He ſolde offices for 750. ducats apeece: hee aduanced his baſtards as his predeceſſors had done: hee made the youngeſt of his ſonnes a Prince of <hi>Sicilie:</hi> his ſecond ſonne called <hi>Caeſar Valentine,</hi> hee made Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall; the eldeſt he made Duke of <hi>Spaine,</hi> he was ſlaine at <hi>Rome:</hi> and his brother Cardinall being wearie of Prieſthood, he eſpouſed one of King <hi>Lewis</hi> his kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: his daughter <hi>Lucrece,</hi> whoſe carnall copulation himſelfe had, was married to three Princes ſucceſſiuely.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19944:37"/> See <hi>Iohn Functius.</hi> He was odious to the whole world: and except God had ſhortned his dayes, by an errour of his Cup-bearer, giuing him a poyſoned Cuppe for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; as he poyſoned ſome of the Cardinalls, he had a purpoſe to haue poyſoned all, whoſe goods he had chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged after their death. See <hi>Guiccinard. li. 5. Onuphrius. Alexander</hi> ſupping vnder a vine neere the <hi>Vatican,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the cooleneſſe of the ayre, he was ſodainely carried away, deſperately ſicke, into the Pallace. The next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he dyed, blacke, ſwolne, and beyond all credit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. <hi>Baleus.</hi> Being ſicke in bed, he ſent his ſeruant <hi>Madena</hi> to his wardrobe, to fetch him a little booke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with gold, and precious ſtones: This booke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all manner of illuſions and inchantments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee would haue beene certified of his life: The ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant running thither, ſaw one in the Popes Chaire, very like himſelfe; whereat being afraid, he ranne to his maſter, pale, and wanne, halfe dead; which the Pope perceiuing, ſuffering him to recouer, willed him to goe the ſecond time; where finding the man ſtill in the Chaire, hee was wonderfully afraide, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of him, what he had to doe there: he anſwered, To fetch a certaine garment for the Pope: At which words the Diuell being then in the Chaire, making an horrible noyſe, ſayd, <hi>I am the Pope.</hi> Theſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Pope. His euill beganne to encreaſe, and Death approached. A ſhort time after, a man apparrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led like a Lackey knocked at the Popes chamber doore, ſaying he muſt needes ſpeake with the Pope. All other drew aſide, and great ſpeech was betweene them. The Pope pleaded, his time was not yet come; for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him nineteene yeers continuance; but the Lackey
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19944:37"/> anſwered; He promiſed him eleauen yeeres and eight moneths, which was accompliſhed, and therefore hee muſt needes die. The Pope pleading for longer time, could not be heard: This talke was heard by them in the next chamber. Finally, as Sathan went away, the Pope with great cries, and ſighes, and fearefull ſobbes, died. See <hi>Onuphrius</hi> the Popes Hiſtoriographer. <hi>Guicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardin. Volateran. Iohn Baleus.</hi> much more theſe Authors report. This Pope had with his ſonne, a daughter, with whom both the father and ſonne lay. <hi>Pontanus,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mozarius</hi> haue left written. 1502.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oppoſition. Iohn Weſelne</hi> an excellent Diuine called <hi>Fax mundi,</hi> againſt the Pope and his doctrine. <hi>Rodolph Agricola</hi> was of the ſame opinion. <hi>Hierom Sauanorola,</hi> with two more Friers, were againſt Iuſtification by workes, merits, pardons; they were hanged, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Sabellicus.</hi> 1499. This Pope cauſed to be cut out, the tongue, and both the hands of <hi>Anthonius Mancenel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> a learned man, becauſe he had written a very elegant Oration againſt the wicked manners, villanies, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt life of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pius</hi> the third, as ſoone as he was made Pope, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended warre with <hi>France,</hi> becauſe they had occupied a part of <hi>Italy</hi> vnder their ſubiection; whom the Pope hoped to haue driuen cleane out of thoſe Lands: hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended alſo an army againſt the Turkes; but while hee went about this, he dyed the 27. day after his election. <hi>Anno</hi> 1503.</p>
               <p>Note from <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Anno</hi> one thouſand, vntill <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth, 1240. the ſpace of 240. yeers,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19944:38"/> the graſhoppers were ſent out from the bottomleſſe pit to deuoure Chriſtians, in ſoule and body. From <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the fourth, vntill <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, 1504. that is, 196. they haue beene permitted to nouriſh, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it, obſcuring all truth, that by falſe doctrine, and lying myracles, they might ſeduce (if it were poſſible) euen the Elect, by Friers Mendicants, and maſſing Prieſts, and haue cruelly put to death the gaine-ſayers: But from that time, vnder <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, and euer ſince, the Papacie hath, and, through Gods mercie, is like to decay ſtill, euen till the comming of Chriſt; who ſhal confound Antechriſt with the breath of his mouth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond, a man (as it were) chiefly borne for warre. Hee beſieged <hi>Rauenna,</hi> and tooke it, and from diuers Princes he tooke diuers Townes, not without great effuſion of bloud. He excommunicated the king of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> and king of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and gaue their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to whomſoever could firſt occupy them. <hi>Maſsius. cap. 20. Chron.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Counſell of <hi>Latterane</hi> was begunne by <hi>Iulius.</hi> 1512. This monſter died the yeare following, after he had begunne the Counſell, hauing committed an in fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of murthers, and wickedneſſes vnheard of before. <hi>Iulian</hi> meaning to goe to warre againſt <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> and <hi>Lewis,</hi> paſſing ouer the bridge, he caſt Saint <hi>Peters</hi> keyes into <hi>Tyber,</hi> and tooke the Sword of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying: <hi>The Keyes of Saint</hi> Peter <hi>ſerue vs to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: it may be Saint</hi> Paules <hi>Sword will doe ſomething.</hi> He diſpenſed with King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight for his marriage: hee excommunicated <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King, and gaue away his kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19944:38"/>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Epigram.</head>
                     <l>By fraud the Merchant <hi>Iulius</hi> rakes in pelfe,</l>
                     <l>For heauen he ſells, yet hath it not himſelfe.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>1513</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth: he gaue himſelfe to pleaſures, and luſts of the fleſh: he had Singers and Muſitians at his Table. He hated mortally the Goſpell, and on a day <hi>Bembo</hi> the Cardinall vttering a thing out of the Goſpell, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, It hath euer ſufficiently beene knowne, what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the fable of Chriſt hath brought vs, and ours. The ſame day that <hi>Leo</hi> made thirty one Cardinalls, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Temple where they were aſſembled, happened ſuch a great tempeſt, which ſhooke and carried away the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of Chriſt out of his Mothers lappe, and the Keyes out of the hands of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> there; 1517. At which very time, <hi>Luther</hi> beganne to thunder againſt the Pope. He commaunded <hi>Luthers</hi> bookes to be burnt at <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> burnt his Cannons, and popiſh Decretalls, at <hi>Wittenberge.</hi> The Pope reioycing at the ouerthrow of the French King, making good cheere, ſodainly died at his Table. <hi>Baleus. 1524. Oppoſition. Picus Mirandola</hi> againſt reall Preſence, the worſhip of the Croſſe, and Images.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſixt ſate two yeeres: the Bookes of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Phiſitian and Magitian were burnt at <hi>Rome;</hi> ſome of which were brought to <hi>Adrian,</hi> whereof hee made great account, and they were, after his death found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his ſecret papers. <hi>Adrian</hi> after hee had perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the truth of the Goſpell (as his predeceſſors) in the perſon of <hi>Luther,</hi> and <hi>Occolampadius</hi> dyed, ſuſpected of poyſon. <hi>Abb. Veſp.</hi> Others ſay, he was too good to be a Pope; for ſeeing the abuſes of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19944:39"/> going about to reforme them, he was taken away by death. 1523. See a Biſhop of their owne <hi>Eſpenſeus,</hi> a learned man, who ſaith that he deliuered by his <hi>Nuncio,</hi> to the aſſembly of the States of <hi>Germany</hi> his reſolution that way. Therefore they would euer ſince chuſe none but <hi>Italians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeauenth ſate eleauen yeeres: The twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of Ianuary following, 1522. the iourney of <hi>Swi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was held at <hi>Lucerne,</hi> where they wholly confirmed the Popes doctrine, and condemned that of the Goſpel. The Pope was beſieged a long time with his Cardinalls in the Caſtle of Saint <hi>Angelo;</hi> hee was taken priſoner by <hi>Charles</hi> Emperour, and was ranſomed with our money from <hi>England,</hi> at 40000. ducats. At <hi>Berne</hi> hee held a Diſputation, wherein <hi>Swinglius, Bucer, Cappo,</hi> and <hi>Blaurer,</hi> vanquiſhed by Scripture the aduerſe part. Finally, they confirmed by the authoritie of the Magiſtrates through all their land, the ſayd Articles; aboliſhed the Maſſe, and threw downe Images and Altars. <hi>Rome</hi> was ſacked by the Emperour more miſerably then euer by <hi>Gothes,</hi> and <hi>Vandalls.</hi> The Pope dyed in the end of September, of a diſeaſe in the ſtomacke: Others thinke he was poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned by the ſmell of a Torch. See <hi>Iohn Paptiſt. Fulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> 1534.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the third ſate fifteene yeeres: King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight baniſhed the Popes authoritie, who challenged to be Supreame head of the Church of <hi>England. Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rochester,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> Chancellour were beheaded, becauſe they would not agree to the Kings Edict. This <hi>Paul</hi> was an Aſtrologian, a Magitian, and a Diuine. Hee had a familiar, one <hi>Denis Senila,</hi> a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19944:39"/> Magitian, whom hee made Cardinall, with one <hi>Gaurice</hi> of <hi>Portugall, Cecius,</hi> and <hi>Mercell,</hi> Negromancers, and wicked villaines. Of theſe hee did inquire the fortunes of himſelfe, and of his baſtards. Hee had a Siſter called <hi>Iulia Ferneſe,</hi> which hee gaue to Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> to be Cardinall and Biſhop of <hi>Hoſtia,</hi> which hee obtained, for theſe are good priſes (or their younger brethren) to maintaine their whooredomes, or that which is worſe: See <hi>Agrippa.</hi> This muttherer poyſoned his mother and nephew, that al the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Ferneſes</hi> might fall vpon him. Hee had another ſiſter, whoſe carnall company hee ſometime had: but becauſe ſhe loued o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers company more then his, hee poyſoned her alſo: He defloured another maid of a noble houſe, pretending to be a Gentleman of the Legats, and promiſed marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, who finding the truth, ſhe ranne madde. Againe, one <hi>Nicholas de Cheſme</hi> finding him one day adulterouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſing his wife <hi>Laurea Ferneſe</hi> (who was alſo the ſaid <hi>Paules</hi> neece) hee wounded ſo well with his dagger, as he carried the markes to his graue. Moreouer, this good father <hi>Paul,</hi> tooke his pleaſure with his daughter <hi>Constance,</hi> and poyſoned her huſband. He alſo had in his Table the number of 45000. whores, of whom he exacted euery moneth tribute, to haue liberty to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their whoredome. See <hi>Baleus,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> captiue. Hee curſed King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and gaue his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to whomſoeuer could get it. He gaue leaue by an Indulgence, to communicate the Lords Supper vnder both kindes, and to eate all manner of meates, at all times. The Miniſters of the <hi>Lantzgraues</hi> Countrey, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed the Indulgence. <hi>Eſtate of the Church.</hi> He ordained the Counſell of <hi>Trent</hi> the firſt of Nouember 1542. The
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19944:40"/> Pope dyed, the tenth of Nouember.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iulius</hi> the third ſate fiue yeeres. Becauſe of auncient cuſtome the Pope might giue his red Hatre to whom he would, he made Cardinall a young boy, called <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent:</hi> The Cardinals being againſt it, asked what he ſaw in this young man that deſerued it. Hee anſwered, I pray you, what found you in me to doe me this honour, to make me Pope, without any deſert? Aduaunce this young man, and he will merit it. He was a ribbald and a mighty blaſphemer: he loued Swines fleſh: his Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Phyſitian ſayd, it was not good for the gout: He cryed out, Bring me my porke fleſh, <hi>All di ſpitto di Deo:</hi> that is, In deſpite of God. At another time for his Peacocke detayned, being very angry, &amp;c. hee ſayd, If God were ſo angry for an Apple, as to caſt our firſt Parents out of Paradiſe, wherefore ſhould it not be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for me, that am his Vicar, to be angry for a Peacock, better then an Apple? He had three bowles at feaſts for euacuation. <hi>Eſtate of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marcellus</hi> the ſecond ſate twenty dayes: he was Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident of the Counſell of <hi>Trent,</hi> where he put out <hi>Iames Nichiantes</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Foſſa Claodia,</hi> becauſe hee would not allow Traditions to be receiued, and allowed with like reuerence as the Goſpell. Alſo <hi>Guillam de Venice</hi> ſayd, that the Counſell of <hi>Venice</hi> was aboue the Pope: and <hi>Vergerius</hi> was alſo put from the Counſell, becauſe he denyed the Legend of Saint <hi>George,</hi> and Saint <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher</hi> to be true, which he proued from <hi>Paul</hi> the third: for he hath comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, that both theſe Legends ſhould be taken out of the Breuiarie, and commanded that all ſuch ſhould be taken out, which were not true. Hee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19944:40"/> died of the Iaundiſe the 20. day after his election. 1555.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the fourth ſate foure yeeres, two moneths, and twenty ſeauen dayes: This Pope inuented a new ſect of Monks, and called them <hi>Ieſuites.</hi> Before he was Pope, hee writ a Booke vnto <hi>Paul</hi> the third, touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church: but being Pope, hee cared neither for Ieſus Chriſt, nor for his Church: In his book he confirmeth almoſt all the points we vſe to reprehend in Poperie. He grieued the people of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe of his warres, and exactions, that ſcarce had hee yeeleded vp the ſpirit, but the <hi>Roman</hi> people, whihc wiſhed death vnto him, becauſe of his warres, and exactions, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies; broke the priſons of the Inquiſitions, deliuered the priſoners, fired the whole building, threw downe the Popes Image, cutting off the head and right hand thereof, which were drawne three dayes together tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Towne, and then caſt into <hi>Tyber.</hi> Hee kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly a Gentlemans wife. Hee vſed to eate Snailes, and to drinke ſtrong wine, called <hi>Magnagarra,</hi> for luſt. Hee died in bed with his whoore. 1565. <hi>Eſtate of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth ſate ſixe yeeres: Hee cauſed to be ſtrangled, the fift of March, 1561. in the night, in Saint <hi>Angelo,</hi> the Cardinall <hi>Charles Caraffe.</hi> He beheaded alſo in another priſon, the County of <hi>Palliane,</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other Cardinalls, ſhewing their bodies the next day vnto the people. He cited the Queene of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> becauſe of the profeſſion of the Goſpell, to anſwer in the Popes Conſiſtorie; and for want of appearance within ſixe moneths, her Countrey to be giuen to the next Conqueror. The fourth of December was ended the Counſel of <hi>Trent,</hi> 1563. which from the beginning
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19944:41"/> to the ending, continued eighteene yeeres, wherein all the Articles of Popiſh doctrine were confirmed. The eight of September <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth died.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pius</hi> the fift ſate ſixe yeeres: <hi>Iohn Functius,</hi> a learned Chronographer, amongſt all of our time was beheaded, becauſe he, with other Preachers of the Goſpell, were againſt the dreames of <hi>Oſiander.</hi> The Pope ſent a great Preſent to the Duke of <hi>Alua,</hi> as a recompence of ſo great paynes he had taken to maintaine the Popedome. He ſent his roaring Bull of <hi>Baſan</hi> againſt Queene <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth.</hi> 1571.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the thirteenth ſate thirteene yeeres. The Pope, by adding of tenne dayes in October, ſo as for the fift they ſhould reckon fifteene: This, to eternize the Popes name, was called the <hi>Gregorian Kallender.</hi> The Pope dayly vrged the performance of his Kallen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in <hi>Germany,</hi> D. <hi>Chytreus</hi> 1585. Whereupon preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſedition burſt out. This Pope renewed the hatred of his predeceſſour <hi>Pius</hi> the fift againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> Firſt, by ſending his great <hi>Armada</hi> into <hi>Ireland;</hi> then, by ſending <hi>Parry,</hi> and others. This Pope had his Concubine before hee was Pope, and after hee was Pope; by whom he had two little ſonnes, which ſayd vnto him ſuch graces, as made him laugh: <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picus</hi> his ſonnes grace was, <hi>That the Pope his Father gaue him fiue thouſand crownes a yeere. M. Cyp. Volater.</hi> He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Rome.</hi> Aprill 11. 1585.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fift ſate ſixe yeeres: This <hi>Foelix,</hi> ſo called before, being a poore mans ſonne, was brought vp by a Gentlewoman ſo long, as he grew proude: then ſhee
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19944:41"/> cauſed him to be beaten: Then hee fled to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Pope tooke him into ſeruice; at the length he made him a Cardinall; and by his good friends in <hi>Spaine</hi> hee was made Pope. <hi>M. Cyp. Volater.</hi> One day talking of his meane birth, he ſaid he came of an illuſtrious houſe: for, ſaid he, the vpper part of the houſe being alwayes torne and vncouered, the Sunne made it moſt glorious with his beames. See <hi>Antonius Caracalla De vitis Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</hi> This Pope excommunicated the King of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and <hi>Condie,</hi> giuing his Countrey to ſuch as could get it; declaring him vncapable of the ſucceſſion of the crowne of <hi>France.</hi> He approued a Nunne, called <hi>Maria de Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione,</hi> who long deluded the people: She grew ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, as the king of <hi>Spaine</hi> inquired of her his good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe for <hi>England</hi> 1588. Shee promiſed good ſucceſſe: and that Duke <hi>Medina,</hi> Generall, (ſhe pronounced open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) ſhould returne a victorious Prince. So proſper all Gods enemies. But the next yeere after, all her holineſſe, falſe miracles, and great diſſimulations were ſoone found out, and ſhe puniſhed for the ſame. See <hi>M. Cyp. Volater.</hi> The moſt Chriſtian Prince of <hi>Condie,</hi> whom the Pope excommunicated, and curſed, was poyſoned. The king of <hi>France,</hi> whom hee alſo excommunicated with many threats, was ſlaine by a <hi>Iacobine</hi> Frier, in his priuy-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; vnder colour of deliuering a letter out of his ſleeue, he drew forth a poyſoned knife out of his ſleeue, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he killed him. D. <hi>Chytreus</hi> 1589. No Religion will ſtay the Papiſts. The Pope at <hi>Rome</hi> made an Oration in the commendation of this Frier, comparing him with <hi>Eleazer,</hi> and <hi>Iudith:</hi> and, not thus ſatisfied, he denyed any honour to be made at his buriall, or any man to pray for him. This Pope died the ſeauen and twenty of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19944:42"/> Auguſt, 1590. He made many new Holidayes, <hi>M. Cyp. Volater.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſeuenth ſate twelue daies: There happened a great earthquake vpon the day of his Election at <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> and <hi>Auſtria.</hi> The next day after his election he fell ſicke, and determined to remoue his Court to the hill of <hi>Quirinus,</hi> a better ayre: but hee tarried, becauſe it was againſt the cuſtome to goe abroad before hee was crowned. But he dyed the twelfth day after. <hi>Arthur Cicer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gregorie</hi> the foureteenth ſate tenne moneths and ten dayes: hee was proclaymed by the high Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, <hi>Chalnut</hi> and <hi>Toures,</hi> an enemy to the common peace, and to the vnion of the Catholique Religion, and to the king and his royall ſeate, adherent to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie of <hi>Spaine,</hi> a fauourer of Rebells, guilty of the moſt cruell, moſt inhumane, and moſt deteſtable death of <hi>Henry</hi> the third moſt Catholique King: Againe, an Act was made againſt the Popes Bulles: hee dyed of a quartane feuer. He was troubled with a continuall flux which he had. <hi>Arthur Cicer.</hi> 1591.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the ninth ſate two moneths and odde dayes, and died being threeſcore and ten yeeres of age: ſo that in the ſpace of foureteene moneths, foure Popes dyed; <hi>Sixtus, Vrban, Gregorie, Innocent,</hi> as it is to be thought, the moſt, or all died of poyſon: for <hi>Bazutus</hi> is not dead, that killed ſixe Popes with poyſon. See the life of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſus</hi> the ſecond. 1591.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clement</hi> the eight ſate nine yeeres: The Earle of <hi>Fuentes</hi> practized with <hi>Lopus,</hi> and promiſed 50000.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19944:42"/> crownes to poyſon Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Hee alſo dealt with <hi>Emmanuel Adrian</hi> to kill the King of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> with the odious ſmell of a poyſoned roſe. <hi>Da. Chytreus. 1594. Iohn Castill</hi> a Scholler of the Ieſuites ſtrucke the King of <hi>Fraunce</hi> with a knife: but the King ſtouping to take vp the Lords before him, hee ſtrucke out one of his teeth, and was apprehended, &amp;c. The King after two yeeres intreating the Pope, was receiued into the lappe of the Church, and declared Chriſtian King of <hi>France,</hi> with condition to receiue the Counſell of <hi>Trent,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the young Prince of <hi>Condie</hi> from the company of Hereticks: That he ſhould reſtore the reuenews, and goods taken from the Biſhops and Abbeys, and teſtifie his conuerſion to the Catholique Princes, &amp;c. <hi>Da. Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treus.</hi> The Pope diſcontented at <hi>Caeſar Eſt,</hi> who enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Empire after the death of the Emperour <hi>Rodolph,</hi> whom he declared his heire in his life time, ſtrucke him with the Thunder-bolt of Excommunication, and made warre vpon him. <hi>Caeſar Eſt</hi> Duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> the matter being taken vp, yeelded <hi>Ferrara</hi> to the Pope, who vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it to the Popedome. Pope <hi>Clement</hi> made thirteene Cardinalls, amongſt whom was <hi>Rob. Bellarmine</hi> Ieſuite. 1599. This yeere 1600. <hi>Richard</hi> L. Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> with two other Commiſſioners. Doctor <hi>Parkins,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Swale,</hi> were ſent in Embaſſage to <hi>Embden,</hi> to treate with the Commiſſioners from the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> and returned the eight of Iuly following. 1600.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> the fift renewed the <hi>Index expurgatorius;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is contayned, MERCVRIVS GALLO-BEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GICVS. The humble ſupplication of <hi>Roger Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> an Engliſh Catholique, vnto the moſt holy Lord
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19944:43"/> Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the fift. <hi>Item,</hi> a little Booke tituled <hi>Marcus Anthonius de Dominicis;</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Spalato,</hi> with others.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>Now to conclude this point by recapitulation. The Popes that claime to be <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſors, you ſee they neither ſucceed in place, as hath beene proued (for ſixe or ſeuen Popes ſate at <hi>Auignon</hi> about foureſcore yeres,) nor in manner of liuing, as by their owne Chronicles, with others doe appeare: for ſome were couetous;</p>
               <p>Couetous: <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight: <hi>Calixt</hi> the third: <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty three: <hi>Boniface</hi> the ninth.</p>
               <p>Proude: <hi>Bennet</hi> the twelfth: <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth: <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> the third: <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth: <hi>Alexander</hi> the third: <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth: <hi>Clement</hi> the fift, ſixt, ſeauenth: <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight: <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Iohn</hi> the three and twenty.</p>
               <p>Ambitious: as may be ſeene ſince about fiue hundred yeeres after Chriſt, when they laboured for ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Policarp</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ieruſalem: Miſda</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome: Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Constance: Pelagius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome: Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> oppoſed by <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great: and <hi>Iohn</hi> the third Biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> See fol. 6.</p>
               <p>Blaſphemers: <hi>Leo</hi> the third: <hi>Iohn</hi> the thirteenth: <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the third: <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth.</p>
               <p>Heretickes: <hi>Leo</hi> the ſeauenth: <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight: <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty three: <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>Schiſmatickes, as two, yea three Popes together; ſome two yeeres, ſixeteene yeeres, ſixe yeeres, twenty yeeres, thirty nine yeeres, ſeuen yeeres, thirteene yeeres: See <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond, third and ſixt: <hi>Hildebrand: Paſchalis: Calixt</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Honorius</hi> the ſecond: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:19944:43"/> the ſecond: <hi>Bennet</hi> the thirteenth: Three Popes together ſeauen yeeres. See <hi>Faelix</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Coniurers: <hi>Siluester</hi> the ſecond, and ſo forth; nine or ten Popes together. See <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth: <hi>Paul</hi> the third: <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt.</p>
               <p>In league with the Diuell: <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt: <hi>Silue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the ſecond.</p>
               <p>Inceſtuous: <hi>Iohn</hi> the thirteenth: <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt: <hi>Paul</hi> the third.</p>
               <p>Sodomites: <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>Whoremongers, <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, and thirteenth: <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> the third: <hi>Paul</hi> the third, and fourth: <hi>Innocent</hi> the fourth: <hi>Clement</hi> the third: <hi>Sergius</hi> the third: <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth: <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirteenth.</p>
               <p>Cruell <hi>Iohn</hi> the foureteenth: <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſecond, and ſixt: <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeuenth: <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt: <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth.</p>
               <p>Murtherers: <hi>Pius</hi> the fourth: <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth: <hi>Stephen</hi> the eight: <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fift: <hi>Gregorie</hi> the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth: <hi>Honorius</hi> the ſecond.</p>
               <p>Poyſoners one of another: <hi>Damaſus</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor</hi> the ſecond, and third: <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the fourth: <hi>Paul</hi> the third.</p>
               <p>Treacherous: <hi>Alexander</hi> the third: <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, and ninth: <hi>Innocent</hi> the ninth.</p>
               <p>Couſoners: <hi>Alexander</hi> the third: <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight: <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the fift: <hi>Benedict</hi> the tenth.</p>
               <p>Warriers, ſetting Princes together by the eares, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſours, <hi>Bennet</hi> the ninth: <hi>Martin</hi> the fourth: <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Innocent</hi> the ſecond and ſeauenth: <hi>Iohn</hi> the eleuenth: <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius</hi> the third: <hi>Paſchal</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Vrban</hi> the third and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19944:44"/> ſixt: <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeauenth: <hi>Gregorie</hi> the foureteenth: yea in the Schiſme of Popes, they curſed and warred one with another. See <hi>Victor</hi> 3. and <hi>Paſchal</hi> 2. as in a fight betweene <hi>Vrban</hi> the ſixt, and <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeauenth, there were miſerably ſlaine two hundred thouſand men and many more, and many beſides were drowned. See <hi>Clemen.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Diuers condemned one anothers Decrees, <hi>Iohn</hi> the twelfth: and vnder <hi>Sergius</hi> the third: <hi>Martine</hi> the fift.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the twenty three, choſe himſelfe Pope, <hi>Damaſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Now to conclude with <hi>Cornelius Agrippa de Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat.</hi> Hee hauing ſpoken of the wickedneſſe of Popes in generall, ſaith; I paſſe by thoſe other monſters of the <hi>Roman</hi> Popes, ſuch as was <hi>Formoſus,</hi> and thoſe nine that followed, which ſometime ruled filthily in the Church. I ſay nothing alſo of thoſe latter Popes, <hi>Paul</hi> the ſecond: <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth: <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt: <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the ſecond; the moſt famous troublers of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world: beſides <hi>Eugenius,</hi> which for breaking faith with the Turke, did caſt all the Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth into moſt mortall and bloudy warres; as if faith were not to be kept with an enemie. Moreouer, how much danger <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt brought to the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, by taking away, by poyſon, <hi>Zizimus Pazaithe,</hi> the Turkes brother, is ſufficiently knowne vnto all men. Thus farre <hi>Cornelius. cap.</hi> 6.</p>
               <p>Thus did not <hi>Peter,</hi> who taught faithfully, preached Chriſt diligently, and ſought and taught peace amongſt men; was holy, humble, and ſober, in conuerſation; and in the end, gaue his life for the truth. The Pope therefore in life, being thus contrary vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> is the ſucceſſour of Antechriſt, not of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:19944:44"/>
               <head>Now come wee to examine the Doctrine:</head>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>And first for <hi>Iuſtification.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for the Law, that ſhould haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs for euer, Chriſt hath ſatisfied his Fathers wrath, and hath fulfilled it for vs; and no man in the world could haue done it but he, <hi>Eſay 53. 5. Hee was wounded for our tranſgreſsions, and by his ſtripes wee are healed. 2 Cor. 5. 11. He which knew no ſinne, was made ſinne for vs, that we might be made the, &amp;c.</hi> Chriſt was made ſinne by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, that we might be made righteous before God, by imputation of his righteouſneſſe to vs; <hi>Rom. 5. 19. As by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners, &amp;c.</hi> Note a compariſon betweene <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Christ, Iob 9. 2. How ſhall man, compared with God, be iuſtified? Rom. 3. 10. 11. 12. They haue gone all out of the way, &amp;c. Rom. 4. 5. To him that worketh not, but beleeueth, &amp;c.</hi> and 5. verſe 1. <hi>Being iuſtified thorow faith, wee &amp;c. Epheſ. 2 8. By grace yee are ſaued through faith, not of your ſelues, &amp;c. Rom. 8. 20. Whom he hath called, them alſo he hath iuſtified. 1 Cor.</hi> 4. 4. See: from theſe places I reaſon thus: If Chriſt hath ſatisfied the Law for vs: If hee be our peace with God: If by his ſtripes we be healed: If his righteouſnes be ours by imputation onely: If by his obedience only we be made righteous: If there be none that can doe good, no not one. If iuſtified thorow faith, wee haue peace with God. If ſaued by grace, not of workes. If
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19944:45"/> neuer ſo righteous, yet wee are not thereby iuſtified. Then our Iuſtfication, is plainly without vs, and it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth onely by Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed, and by faith receined. Though theſe be as euident as the Sunne at noone, yet they cauill with vs from other places of Scripture, to maintaine Iuſtification from our ſelues, or at leaſt to part ſtakes with Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Papiſts firſt place <hi>Pſal. 7. 8 Iudge me, O Lord, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my righteouſneſſe. Solut.</hi> This is not ſpoken of our righteouſneſſe before God: but <hi>Dauid</hi> being falſly accuſed vnto <hi>Saul,</hi> by his enemies (his heart being free from any intention of euill againſt him) deſires God to be Iudge betweene him, and them; and therefore this ſerueth not for the Iuſtification of a ſinner before God.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond place, 2 <hi>Corint 4 14. Our light afflictions which are but for a moment, cauſeth vnto vs a farre more excellent weight of glorie.</hi> If afflictions (ſay they) worke our ſaluation, much more good workes. <hi>Solut.</hi> Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions (ſay we) worke our ſaluation, not as cauſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing it, but as meanes directing vs thereto. <hi>Bernard.</hi> They be <hi>via regni, non cauſa regnandi. Pſalme 119. 71. It is good for me that I haue beene in trouble; for, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Of Sacraments, the number.</head>
                  <p>The Papiſts teach ſeauen Sacraments, contrary to Scripture, by a fooliſh myſticall taking the number of ſeauen in Scripture, as a number of perfection: as it was ſaid to <hi>Naaman. 2 King. 5. 10. Goe waſh ſeauentimes.</hi> Againe, <hi>Iob 4. 2. Offered ſeauen Bullockes, and ſeauen Rammes, ſeauen Starres, ſeauen Candleſtickes:</hi> Theſe are too idle to be anſwered, and therefore I leaue them to former anſwers: for this number may as well ferue for a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19944:45"/> myſterie of iniquitie, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17. 18. Sacraments, both in the old and new Teſtament, were of Gods ordinance; men may not make Sacraments. Chriſt putting an end to the olde Teſtament, was the Authour of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the new Teſtament: and appointing outward ſignes of holy things, hee inſtituted two, Baptiſme, and the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; no more are to be found in the new Teſtament of his making, or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. The firſt he ſanctified in his owne perſon, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 16. for he was baptized of <hi>Iohn:</hi> The ſame he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and commanded to his Apoſtles, after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. The Lords Supper: this he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, and miniſtred in his owne perſon alſo, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 19. commaunding to doe this in the remembrance of him. The remiſſion of ſinnes is repreſented in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38: The death of Chriſt is ſet forth in the Lords Supper, 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 11. 26. Whereby our faith is ſtrengthened, and our hope confirmed in the promiſes of God. The like commendation is not giuen of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Sacraments. Many other ceremonies Chriſt vſed; but hee hath not layd his commandement vpon them as vpon theſe. Thus our doctrine for the number, is more auncient then the Churches of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Of Baptiſme.</head>
                  <p>For the outward ſigne thereof, we haue onely water, according to Chriſts Inſtitution; repreſenting the bloud of Chriſt, in waſhing away of our ſinnes: For the forme we baptize onely, <hi>In the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy-Ghost,</hi> according to Chriſts commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. Papiſts (to omit their trifling about God-fathers and God-mothers) that Fathers nor
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19944:46"/> Mothers ſhould not be witneſſes to their children. 936. that man &amp; wife may not anſwer for one child: that goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſips may not marry, nor Monckes nor Nunnes to be Goſſips, &amp;c. None are to be baptized before the Prieſts, through their coniurations, breathings, ſpittings, and ſalting, doe driue the Diuell out of them. Pope <hi>Celestine 428. Clement</hi> commanded Oyle and Creame to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the forehead, and to be croſſed therewith: if this be not to be ſubiect to the curſe of God, for adding to the word, &amp;c. Thus our doctrine and vſe, for Baptiſme, and the ceremonies thereof, is more ancient then the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Supper, or EVCHARIST.</head>
                  <p>For this we haue the Sacramentall ſignes, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Elements, Bread and Wine, repreſenting the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Bloud of Chriſt, offered to the faithfull, with the ſignes, for the feeding of their ſoules, and ſtrengthening of their faith, and putting them in mind of the precious bloud-ſhed in his bitter death and paſſion, according to Chriſts inſtitution. Papiſts miniſter this Sacrament but in one kinde, that is, Bread onely; for (ſay they) Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are not bound by any commandement of God, to receiue the Sacrament in both kindes. Councel of <hi>Trent cap. 21. Bellarmine lib. 4. cap. 20. De Euchariſt,</hi> and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> Though Chriſt ordayned the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in both kindes, and the eldeſt Churches did ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it; yet for all that, they ſhall be puniſhed as Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, that doe miniſter or receiue it. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 13. See their proofes. <hi>Luke 24. 30. Chriſt appearing to the two Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples going to Emaus, entring into an houſe, as he ſate at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he tooke the Bread, and gaue thanks;</hi> therefore one kind
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19944:46"/> is ſufficient. Againe, <hi>Acts 2. 24. And they continued in the Apoſtles doctrine, and in fellowſhip, and in breaking of bread, and in prayer. Solut.</hi> There is no reaſon to vnderſtand theſe places of the breaking of bread in the Sacrament, but in vſuall repaſt. As for <hi>Luke</hi> 24. Chriſt was not miniſtring the Sacrament, for the two Diſciples inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Supper; and Chriſt (as his manner was) gaue thankes, and brake the bread, and they by this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, he vaniſhed out of their ſight. Againe, if this had been the Sacrament, Chriſt had not ſaid true, when vpon the Croſſe (before he gaue vp the Ghoſt) he ſaid, <hi>All things are fulfilled. Iohn</hi> 19. 29. Againe, <hi>Matth. 26. 29. I ſay vnto you, I will not drinke of the fruit of the Vine tree:</hi> If not drinke, then not eate. For the place, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 24. This proues no ſacramentall eating; but continuing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, according to their Maſters commandement, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the comming of the Holy Ghoſt, they did eate and drinke together: expounded in the ſixe and forty verſe, breaking bread at home, did eate their meate together with gladneſſe, and ſingleneſſe of heart. For <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. 11. It maketh as little to the Sacrament, as yet being not inſtituted; and Chriſt expoundeth himſelfe in verſe 63. ſaying, <hi>The words that I ſpeake vnto you, are ſpirit and life.</hi> Beſides, if they will admit this place to be ſpoken of the Sacrament, then they are caſt, in receiuing in one kind: for there he neuer ſpeaketh of Bread, but he ſpeaketh of Drinke alſo. So that wee conclude in the Inſtitution of the Supper, according to the analogie of the Signes, Chriſt had reſpect vnto our full nouriſhment, Bread &amp; Drinke, that ſo wee might finde in Chriſt, whatſoeuer is needefull to ſaluation; for no man can liue with Bread alone, and although Chriſt teach vs to pray for
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19944:47"/> daily bread (which is a maruell you heere eſcaped) yet by <hi>Synechdoche,</hi> hee meaneth drinke alſo, and all things neceſſary to this preſent life. Note we heere, while Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts will giue but Bread alone (we will beate them with their owne weapon:) They falſly charge vs in our communion, that we giue but a drie morſel, they giuing onely Bread to the people, ſhould choake them, but that they are conſtrayned to giue a little Wine (not as any part of the Sacrament) but to helpe downe their breaden god, to his place.</p>
                  <p>Thus our doctrine and practiſe in the vſe of this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, is farre more auncient, being from Chriſt, and the Scriptures, then theirs being from men, in one kind, about the yeere 1552. in the Counſell of <hi>Trent. Item,</hi> in the Counſell of <hi>Constance</hi> before, 1416. where they curſed all thoſe that ſhould ſay it was lawfull to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate in both kindes: and yet by an Indulgence, he gaue leaue to them of <hi>Almaine</hi> to communicate in both kindes. See <hi>Paul</hi> the third: therefore the Pope may adde and take away at pleaſure, but not without Gods curſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Reall Preſence.</head>
                  <p>We teach, that at the Lords Table, the Bread and Wine, muſt not be conſidered barely in themſelues, but as outward ſignes, hauing relation to the Body and Bloud of Chriſt, ariſing from the very Inſtitution of the Sacrament: That when the Bread and Wine, are preſent to the hand and mouth; at the very ſame time, the Body and Bloud of Chriſt are preſent to the minde. Thus, and no otherwiſe, is Chriſt truly preſent with the Signes, to the beleeuing hearts of the Communicants. So <hi>Paul 1 Corinth. 10. 16. The Cuppe of bleſsing which wee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19944:47"/> bleſſe, is it not the Communion of the Bloud of Christ? The Bread which we breake, is it not the Communion of the Body of Christ?</hi> This Communion is double: Firſt, of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, with Chriſt by faith; Secondly, of the faithfull among themſelues, through loue. Both theſe are my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall. Againe, if the fleſhly body be in the Sacrament; then is it eaten and torne with the teeth. <hi>Auguſtine. Why prepareſt thou thy teeth and thy belly? beleeue, and thou hast eaten.</hi> Againe, <hi>Auguſt. Chriſt, according to his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, prouidence, and grace, is preſent with vs to the end of the world: but according to his aſſumed fleſh, he is not alwayes with vs. Actes 1. 11. This Ieſus which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vp from you into Heauen, ſhall ſo come, euen as yee haue ſeene him goe into Heauen. Matth. 26. 11. The poore yee ſhall haue alwayes, but me ſhall yee not haue alwayes. Reuelation 1. 7. Behold, he commeth in the Cloudes, and all eyes ſhall ſee him, euen they that haue pierced him.</hi> Moreouer, it ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth an Article of our faith, which ſaith, <hi>He ſitteth at the right hand of his Father, &amp;c. Cirill</hi> ſayth, Hee is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in Body, and preſent in Vertue, that hath his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions. Papiſts alledge againſt this doctrine, <hi>Iohn 6. 55. My fleſh is meate indeed, and my bloud is drinke indeed: Ergo</hi> (ſay they) Chriſts body muſt be eaten with the mouth. The very Capernaites counted this abſurd. See Chriſts anſwer verſe. 62. 63. See alſo the anſwer of this place before; and in the title of the Supper. Beſides, this Chapter muſt be vnderſtoode of a ſpirituall eating of Chriſt by faith, whether in the Sacrament, or without. Againe, heere is proued both kindes: If of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vpon this place ſaith; <hi>This is to eate his fleſh, and drinke his bloud, to abide in Chriſt, and to haue him abiding in vs.</hi> This may be done without a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19944:48"/> 
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> not neceſſary to be vnderſtood of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. That it muſt be vnderſtood ſpiritually, Chriſt tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth in verſ. 35. <hi>He that commeth to mee, ſhall not hunger, and he that beleeueth in me, ſhall neuer thirſt.</hi> To eate then, and to drinke Chriſt, is to beleeue in him; and verſe 63. he ſaith, <hi>The words which I ſpeake, are ſpirit and life,</hi> that is ſpiritually to be vnderſtood. <hi>Bernard.</hi> What is it to eate his fleſh, and drinke his bloud, but to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with his Paſſion, and to imitate that conuerſation which hee vſed in the fleſh? The other places alledged by them, may receiue anſwer from theſe, becauſe I will not be troubled with them (in this age, and weakeneſſe,) and are alledged by them, of ſome through ignorance, of other maliciouſly ſtriuing againſt the ſtreame of their owne knowledge. To this <hi>Ergo,</hi> as to the other, I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme our Doctrine to be more auncient then theirs; as from Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and Scriptures, and of a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter foundation. No queſtion was heereof for the ſpace of 1060. yeeres, vntill <hi>Nicholas</hi> the ſecond.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
                  <p>By this the Papiſts meane a changing of the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine, into the Body and Bloud of Chriſt: ſo as after the words of conſecration, there remaines no Bread, but the very Body and Bloud of Chriſt, borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and who ſhall ſay to the contrary, let him be accurſed: Counſell of <hi>Trent.</hi> 1550. attempted before 1212, but oppoſed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Popiſh Reaſons.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matthew</hi> 17. Chriſt transfigured his Body vpon the Mount: <hi>Ergo</hi> hee is able to exhibite his Body vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of Bread and Wine. <hi>Anſ.</hi> The queſtion
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19944:48"/> is not ſo much of his power, as of his will. <hi>Pſal. 135. 6. Whatſoeuer the Lord would, that did he in heauen and earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond place, <hi>Iob. 2. 7. He turned water into Wine:</hi> then we need not doubt how he turned the Bread into his Body. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> In turning Water into Wine, he left it to the Iudgement of our ſenſes, &amp;c. But Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Recuſants doe not feele the rawe fleſh of Chriſts Body, though they teach, they teare it with their teeth: and to feed vpon accidents, is no nouriſhment. Againe, Tranſubſtantiation ouerturneth the very Supper of our Lord: for in euery Sacrament, there muſt be a Signe. Againe, it taketh away the nouriſhment of the Soule vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall life; for in Tranſubſtantiation there remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth onely the fleſhly body of Chriſt. Councell of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> As the fleſh of our Lord was vnited, by the Spirit, to the diuine nature: ſo the Bread of the Euchariſt, the image of his fleſh, being ſanctified by the comming of the Holy-Ghoſt, is become the diuine Body. Againe, they hold the Bread conſecrated, though not ſpent at once, but reſerued and kept in boxes, pipes, and other veſſells of the Church, for dayes, weeks, and moneths, to be carried to the ſicke, or other vſes, are ſtill the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Body and Bloud of Chriſt. Counſell of <hi>Trent. Seſſ. 13. cap.</hi> 47. Then, though it ſhould ſtincke, or grow full of wormes, or dogges or Mice eate it, yet it is his Body. Thus Chriſts Body muſt be ſubiect to theſe inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Alſo it is bound againe as in his graue, or worſe pinched, againſt the nature of a fleſhly body. There was no publique Lawe for this deuice, vntill the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of <hi>Latterane,</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1215. Whereupon, in this, as in the reſt, wee conclude with the Scriptures, and Fathers; that the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19944:49"/> myſticall ſignes after Conſecration looſe not their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per nature. <hi>Theodoret. Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. So as our doctrine is more ancient, as from Chriſt, his Apoſtles and Scriptures. See the fruits of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation in the Hiſtorie of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeauenth, who caſt the Hoſte into the fire, becauſe it would giue no anſwere.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Againſt Images.</head>
                  <p>Papiſts make a great difference betweene an Image and an Idoll: <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſay they, is the true ſimilitude of a thing; but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in Latine, <hi>Similacrum;</hi> doth repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that which it is not: as were the Idolls of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Minerua,</hi> women-gods, meere deuiſed things of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. Images, ſay they, we haue, but no Idolls. <hi>Bellar. cap.</hi> 5. Their proofes 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 19. An Idoll is nothing,</hi> that is, repreſenteth nothing, ſuch were the heathen I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolls. But the place is not ſo to be vnderſtood: for ſo he ſaith of the things that are offered vnto them, which were not made to repreſent any thing; neither were it needefull to ſhunne Idoll ſacrifice, or to abhorre the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, but that they are abuſed, and turned to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Idols, as it followeth there, verſe 20. Therefore it is not ſaid to be nothing, or offenſiue being but wood, or ſtone, or ſuch like, but becauſe it is abuſed to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. Againe, all the pictures of the Heathen were not Idolls in this ſence, becauſe they repreſented nothing; For <hi>Iupiter, Mars, Apollo, Hercules,</hi> whoſe Images they had, were men ſometime liuing. Moreouer, they haue Images repreſenting nothing; as of Angels, of God the Father, and of the Holy-Ghoſt, which haue no ſhape, or likeneſſe. <hi>Deuter. 4. 15. 16. Exod. 33. 20. Micha.</hi> 5. 13.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19944:49"/> where Idolls and Images are alike condemned. So haue they alſo imagined Saints, as Saint <hi>George,</hi> and Saint <hi>Chriſtopher:</hi> for there were neuer any ſuch. And the Pope himſelfe commaunded them to be put out of the Decretalls. See Pope <hi>Marcellus 2. Paul</hi> 2. and therefore they haue Idolls by their owne interpretation, as well as the Heathen: but indeede there is no ſuch difference in the Greeke names, which are indifferently taken in Scripture, <hi>Romans 1. 23. Paul</hi> calleth the Gentiles, Idols, Images. <hi>They turned the glory of the immortall God into the Image of a corruptible man, birds, beaſts, &amp;c.</hi> The word ther is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: Againe, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 9. 20. ſpeaketh of them that continued to worſhip Diuells, and Idolls of golde and ſiluer, &amp;c. it muſt needes be meant of Papiſts. We deny not Images for ciuill vſes, <hi>Luke</hi> 20. 24. or ſuch as God hath commanded to be vſed, but to be vſed in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, or in Temples, we vtterly deny, <hi>Exod. 20. 4. Thou ſhalt make to thy ſelfe no grauen Image, nor the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp;c.</hi> If they ſay, as before, of any falſe gods, they haue their anſwer before; and the Roman Catechiſme, on the ſecond Commandement, ſaith it muſt be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of the true <hi>Iehoua,</hi> and it forbids vs to reſemble God, either in his nature, property, or workes, <hi>Deut. 4. 15. Exodus 40. 18. To whom will yee liken God? or what ſimilitude will ye ſet vp vnto him? Pſal. 97. 7. Confounded be all they that worſhip grauen Images: worſhip him all ye gods. Tertul. de Idolis cap.</hi> 3. ſaith, That euery forme or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, is to be termed an Idoll. And <hi>Iſiod. etenim libr.</hi> 8. ſaith, that the heathen vſed the names of Image &amp; Idoll, indifferently, in one, and the ſame ſignification, <hi>Acts 7. 41. Stephen</hi> called the golden Calfe an Idoll. <hi>Hier.</hi> ſaith that Idols are Images of dead men. <hi>Lactantius, li.</hi> 2.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19944:50"/> 
                     <hi>cap.</hi> 19. ſayth, <hi>Where Images are for Religion, there is no Religion. Epiphanius</hi> ſaith, It is againſt the authority of the Scriptures, to ſee the Image of Chriſt, or of any Saint hanging in the Church. <hi>Epiſt. ad Iohannem Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> And further he ſaith, in the ſeauenth Counſell of <hi>Conſtantinople: Be mindefull (beloued children) not to bring Images into the Church, &amp;c. nor let them be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in common houſes; for it is not meete a Christian ſhould be occupyed by the eyes, but by the meditation of the minde.</hi> To conclude this poynt, 1 <hi>Iohn 5. verſe 21. Babes, keepe your ſelues from Images.</hi> Papiſts obiect, they doe not worſhip the Image; then doe they not obey the Popes Decrees: for in the ſecond Counſell of <hi>Nice,</hi> it was decreed, That the Image of God ſhould be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with the ſame honour, that God himſelfe was worſhipped, 787. yeeres after Chriſt. <hi>Rhemes Teſtament</hi> in the Annotations vpon the <hi>Acts,</hi> cha. 17. verſe 29. doe allow the Image of God to be pictured like an old man, with grey haires, in their Churches; againſt Scriptures, and Fathers. But in the fourth Counſell of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> the 7. generall, before the <hi>Nicene</hi> thirty nine yeeres, vnder <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the fift Emperour, it was decreed: If any man from henceforth, ſhall dare to make him an Image, to worſhip it in the Church, or ſet it vp in his houſe, or keepe it ſecretly; if hee be of the Clergie, let him be depoſed; if a Lay man, accurſed be hee, <hi>Anno</hi> 748. So as, doe they worſhip the Image, or God, in, or before the Image, they are condemned by Scripture, Antiquity, Counſells and Fathers, whatſoeuer reaſons they haue to the contrary, as idle, and to no purpoſe. For Counſels, where at one was 330 Biſhops, &amp;c. Kings, Emperours, with the aduice of their Biſhops, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19944:50"/> men, haue condemned Images; though the latter Popes, with the former, to maintaine their pompe, and keep the people occupied, haue taken from them Gods Booke, and haue ſet them vp theſe, as Babes to play withall, and to keepe them in perpetuall blindneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Worſhipping of Saints, and Prayers to them.</head>
                  <p>The Papiſts teach, That Saints departed, are with great profit and pietie called vpon, and prayed vnto; and that it is not onely lawfull, but godly ſo to doe. <hi>Rhemiſts 1. Tim. 2. Sect. 4. Bellarm. cap. 19. De Sanctorum beati.</hi> But they ſay they pray to them as Interceſſours onely: neyther doe they make them immediate Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, but through Chriſt; concluding their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Per Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum. Bellarmin.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. This is not true; for you deſire not them onely to pray for you, but to haue mercy on you. As, O bleſſed <hi>Mary,</hi> haue mercy vpon vs, preſerue thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, &amp;c. <hi>Gabriel Beet,</hi> one of your owne, is not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to write, That God hath diuided his Kingdome, reſeruing Iuſtice to himſelfe, hath left mercie to the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Marie;</hi> and a blaſphemous Hymne: By the right of a Mother, Commaund the Redeemer. <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſaith, Let <hi>Mary</hi> be had in honour, but let the Father, Sonne, and Holy-Ghoſt be adored: Let no man adore <hi>Mary,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 79. Againe, it is falſe that they alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude their prayers, <hi>Per Chriſtum Dominum noſtrum:</hi> For, in that blaſphemous prayer of <hi>Thomas,</hi> they pray:
<q>
                        <l>Thou by the bloud of <hi>Thomas,</hi> which he for vs did ſpend,</l>
                        <l>Make vs (O Chriſt) to climbe where <hi>Thomas</hi> did aſcend.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Heere they aske eternall life, by the bloud of <hi>Thomas:</hi>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19944:51"/> So ſome of the company haue abuſed the Pſalmes, and the Lords Prayer, by placing our Lady, and other Saints in the roome of God.</p>
                  <p>Papiſts places, <hi>Exod. 32. 13. Moſes</hi> prayer. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> thy ſeruants. <hi>Moſes</hi> (ſay they) hopeth to haue his prayer heard by their merits. <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Anſwer. <hi>Moſes</hi> rehearſeth onely the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made to them, and their ſeed, as it followeth there; <hi>Moſes</hi> therefore pleadeth not their merits, but Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to them. Againe (ſay they) the Saints on earth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire one anothers prayers, <hi>Romans 15. 30. Epheſians 6. 18. Coloſsians 4. 3. Ergo:</hi> much more may wee deſire the prayers of the Saints departed. <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Anſwer. To pray one for another, hath a Commandement, the Lords prayer. <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi> and in other places of Scripture: It is a dutie of charity: But to requeſt the Prayers of Saints departed, hath no warrant. Againe, wee pray one for another heere, becauſe wee know one anothers neceſſities. Prayer is to be made to God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, (and to no creature beſides) as a principall part of his worſhip, <hi>Eſay 42. 8. My glorie will I not giue to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, neyther my prayſe to grauen images. Romans 10. 14. How ſhall they call vpon him on whom they haue not belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?</hi> but we muſt beleeue only in God; <hi>Ergo:</hi> no pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be made, but to him. The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> ſay they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in our Lady: <hi>Ergo,</hi> they may pray to her. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Curſed are they that put any confidence in man, &amp;c. Ieremy</hi> 17. 5. Againe, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 4. 16. we are willed to goe with boldneſſe to the Throne of grace; that wee may receiue mercie, and finde grace to helpe in the time of neede: <hi>Ergo,</hi> no neede of Saints inuocation. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: He for whom no man prayeth, but himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19944:51"/> for all; he is the onely Mediatour: <hi>Ergo</hi> Saints are not to be prayed vnto, <hi>lib. 2. contra Permin. cap. 8. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen Counſell 2. artic. 2. Tharaſius</hi> Preſident of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſaith; We doe plainely teſtifie that we repoſe and referre our faith, and truſt onely in God: <hi>Ergo,</hi> in no Saints or Angells. That the Saints pray for vs, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge theſe places, 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 15. I will endeuour therefore alwayes, that ye alſo may be able to haue remembrance of theſe things after my departure:</hi> where he promiſeth, ſaith the <hi>Rhemiſts,</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine cap.</hi> 18. to be carefull, and to pray for them after his departure. This the Apoſtle performeth, in writing this Epiſtle, that they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the things that hee taught them, when hee was gone from them, not to pray vnto him after hee was dead, or hee to pray for them: For in verſe 13. he ſaith, <hi>I thinke it meete, ſo long as I am in this Tabernacle, to ſtirre you vp, by putting you in remembrance: Ergo,</hi> not after his diſſolution. Againe, they alledge the <hi>Reuelation 5. 8. The foure and twentie Elders are ſayd to haue golden vialls full of odours,</hi> which are the prayers of the Saints, <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts: Ergo,</hi> The Saints pray for vs. Anſwer. This tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs not that Saints pray for vs, and therefore wee muſt pray to them: But this is an action of the whole Church of God Triumphant, and Militant, which do offer vp their prayers, and thankeſ giuings of ſweete o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour vnto Chriſt, out of the ſanctified vialls of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hearts, prophecied by <hi>Malachy 3. verſes</hi> 3. 4. See <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus lib. 4. cap.</hi> 33. and 34. Againe, <hi>Tertull. lib. 4. contra Marcianum. Pſal. 141. 2. Let my prayers be directed in thy ſight, as the incenſe, and the lifting vp of my hands, as the euening Sacrifice.</hi> See 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 9. ſpeaking to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſaith, <hi>You are a royall Prieſthood, &amp;c.</hi> The Saints in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19944:52"/> heauen pray not for any man in particular, <hi>Eſay</hi> 63. 16. The Church ſaith to God, <hi>Doubtleſſe thou art our Father, though</hi> Abraham <hi>be ignorant of vs, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>knowes vs not.</hi> Now if <hi>Abraham,</hi> nor <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo great Patriarkes, then not <hi>Mary, Peter, Paul, &amp;c. Auguſtine</hi> out of the words of <hi>Eſay</hi> aboue, ſaith, <hi>If ſo great Patriarkes were ignorant what became of the people which were borne of their loynes, how is it like that other dead can be preſent, to vnderſtand, and to be helping to mens affaires? Pſalme 73. verſe 25. Whom haue I in heauen but thee? and there is none on earth, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, <hi>If the ſoules of the dead were preſent at the affaires of the liuing, my deuout Mother would neuer a night be from mee, who followed mee in her life,</hi> &amp;c. Againe, <hi>Tractat. Iohn</hi> 22. This ſaith thy Sauiour. Thou haſt no whither to goe but to me: Thou haſt no way to goe but by mee. Againe, 1 <hi>Iohn 21. If any man ſinne, &amp;c.</hi> Vpon theſe words he ſayth. He ſaid not, <hi>Yee haue;</hi> but being ſuch an Apoſtle, ſaid, <hi>We haue. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome de defectu Euangel.</hi> ſayth, <hi>Thou haſt no neede of Patrons, to goe to God, that thou ſhouldest ſearch out others: But though thou be alone, and want a patron, and by thy ſelfe; Pray vnto God, and thou ſhalt obtaine thy deſire.</hi> Thus wee conclude our religion in this point, to be more ancient, and true then theirs; as grounded vpon Chriſt, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and Scriptures.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Purgatorie.</head>
                  <p>Papiſts affirme, that there is a certaine infernall place in the earth called <hi>Purgatory,</hi> in the which, as in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon-houſe, the ſoules which were not fully purged in this life, are there cleanſed and purged by fire, before they can be receiued into heauen. <hi>Bellarm. De Purgator.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19944:52"/> Rhemiſts, Matth. 12. Sect</hi> 9. The proofes <hi>Zachar. 9. 11. Thou haſt looſened thy priſoners out of the pit, wherein was no water. Pſal. 66. 12. Wee went through fire and water, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe, and ſuch like places are alledged. For the place of <hi>Zacharie,</hi> the Ieſuite hath alledged it already; for <hi>Lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus patrum,</hi> and now he maketh it ſerue for Purgatorie. But Purgatorie and <hi>Lymbus patrum,</hi> are diuerſe, and contrary things. For <hi>Lymbus patrum</hi> was onely for thoſe (as they ſay) that liued before Chriſt, but Purgatory be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne ſince. <hi>Lymbus</hi> was voyde of paine, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as they confeſſe; ſo is not Purgatorie. So as the place cannot ſignifie both. But they wreſt Scripture at pleaſure. Indeed the place intendeth no ſuch thing: but it ſetteth forth the afflictions, and miſeries of this life. For ſo <hi>Auguſtine De Ciuitate Dei, cap.</hi> 35. By the pit without water, hee vnderſtandeth the drie and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren dungeon of humane miſery, where there is no ſpring of Iuſtice, but the puddle and mire of iniquitie, that is, the Prophet ſpeaketh of the deliuerance of the people from their cruell and vniuſt bondage. Againe, out of the <hi>Pſalme 86. 13. Thou haſt deliuered my ſoule from the loweſt graue. What elſe</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>is the loweſt pit or graue, but the loweſt degree of miſerie? &amp;c. 1 Corinth.</hi> 3. 13. is their maine place for Purgatorie. <hi>The fire ſhall trie euery mans worke. If any mans worke burne, he ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer loſſe, but hee ſhall ſaue himſelfe: yet as it were thorow fire. Bellarmine,</hi> by Fire vnderſtandeth the flames of Purgatorie; by wood, ſtubble, ſtraw, he vnderſtandeth ſinnes, which muſt be purged by fire. Anſwer. By the precious matter is not vnderſtood the workes of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, but the preaching of ſound doctrine, by ſtraw, and other combuſtible matter, is meant the affectation
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19944:53"/> of eloquence, and corrupt teaching of the truth: yet holding the foundation: Not veniall ſinnes, as they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme; and this <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo granteth. Secondly, Fire in this place is taken allegorically; that is, by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, as the reſt of the words: neither can it be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of their Purgatorie, becauſe it trieth the workes onely, not the perſons, as well the beſt matter as the baſe. But all ſhall not paſſe thorow Purgatory, by their owne confeſſion: and therefore they ſhift it off with a double ſence, verſe 13. the fire they take for Gods ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: in the verſe 15. for the flames of Purgatorie. As if in Allegories the ſame words and place ſhould admit a double ſence. <hi>The day ſhall declare it: Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, The day of Chriſts comming; <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> vnderſtand it, the particular day of euery mans death: ſo well they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together. But the meaning is apparant, that the day, that is, the time ſhall declare it: for God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted a time, to examine euery mans doctrine by fire; which is nothing elſe, but the Iudgement of God, by the fire of his word: whereby euery man in the day of his calling and conuerſion ſhall know whether hee hath preached aright, or no.</p>
                  <p>We acknowledge no ſuch place as Purgatorie; as a third place, but Heauen, or Hell, according to the Scriptures. Our purgation is in this life, afflictions, and faith in the bloud of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn 1. 7. Christs bloud purgeth vs from all our ſinnes. Hebr. 9. 14. It purgeth our conſciences from dead workes.</hi> Wee acknowledge but two ſorts of men, <hi>Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 12. 14. good, or bad, <hi>He that beleeueth, ſhall be ſaued; he that beleeueth not, ſhall be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Marke 10. 16. Luke 16. 26. Iohn 3. 30. Auguſtine</hi> conſenteth with vs, ſaying; There is no middle or third
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19944:53"/> place: but he muſt needs be with the Diuell, that is not with Chriſt, <hi>Lib. 1. cap. De Pecc. remiſs.</hi> Againe, the third place beſides heauen, and hell, we are vtterly ignorant of: nay, wee finde not in Scripture that there is any. <hi>Item, 2 Corint. 5. 10. Apocal. 14. 13. Bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord, they reſt from their labours: Ergo,</hi> no Purgatorie. <hi>Auguſt. Homil. 50. Tom.</hi> 10. After this life there remaynes no compunction, no ſatisfaction. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>Auguſt. Enchirid. cap.</hi> 115. Heere is all remiſſion of ſinnes. Heere be tentations that moue vs to ſinne: Laſtly, heere is the euill from which we deſire to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered: but there is none of all theſe. Againe, wee are not heere without ſinne, but wee ſhall goe hence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne: <hi>Ergo,</hi> no neede of Purgatorie. <hi>De verbis Apoſtoli Serm. 3. Cirill. libr.</hi> 3. vpon <hi>Eſay</hi> ſayth: They which are once dead, can adde nothing to the things which they haue done, but ſhall remaine as they were left, and wait for the time of the laſt Iudgement. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom. ad populum Antiochenum, Homil.</hi> 22. ſayth: After the end of this life, there is no occaſion of merits. <hi>Hebrews 1. 3. Chriſt hath purged our ſinnes, by himſelfe.</hi> Counſell <hi>Aquiſgrane, lib. 1. cap.</hi> 1. ſpeaketh of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, two in this life, one in the life to come, moſt grieuous. Of the two heere the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: <hi>If wee would iudge our ſelues, we ſhould not be, &amp;c.</hi> The firſt is the puniſhment wherein euery ſinner taketh reuenge of himſelfe: The ſecond, but when wee are iudged of God, wee are chaſtiſed, &amp;c. This is the puniſhment which God in mercy doth lay vpon ſinners in this world. The third is moſt fearefull and terrible; not in this world, but in the next. <hi>Depart from me, &amp;c. Ergo,</hi> no Purgatorie. The Papiſts can neuer agree of the place,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19944:54"/> nor continuance of time, how long? And thus we ſtill conclude, that their doctrine is Antichriſtian, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Scripture, and all antiquitie, and Fathers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Merits.</head>
                  <p>By Merits wee vnderſtand any thing, or worke, whereby Gods fauour, and life eternall, from the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the worke binding God, &amp;c. Merits are two-fold: one of the perſon, another of the worke. Of the perſon dying after Baptiſme: Of the worke, by the condigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, yea more, Supererrogation. I omit their idle and blaſphemous ſpeeches, and proofes, and come to the Anſwere. Wee renounce all perſonall merits of any meere man: therefore of Infants that cannot worke; alſo of workes done by them: Onely wee acknowledge Chriſts workes to merite, which are made ours by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation. But Papiſts will be ſaued by their owne workes. See <hi>Exod.</hi> chap. 20. 8. <hi>I will ſhew mercy to them that loue mee, and keepe my commandements:</hi> If theſe muſt haue mercy, who can pleade merits? <hi>Romans 6. 23. The wages of ſinne is death, but eternall life is the gift of God, thorow Ieſus Chriſt. Epheſ. 2. 8. 10. By grace ye are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued through faith, not of your ſelues: it is the gift of God, &amp;c. Romans 8. 18. The ſufferings of this life are not worthy, &amp;c. Titus 3. 5. We are ſaued, not by workes which wee wrought, but according to his mercy, &amp;c.</hi> Merit hath no place where mercie is required. See Fathers. <hi>Bernard.</hi> Thoſe which wee call Merits, are the way to the Kingdome, not the cauſe of raigning. <hi>Auguſtine, All my hope is in the death of my Lord: His death is my merit, my merit is the paſsion of my Lord. Manuel,</hi> chapter two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Againe: He crowneth thee, becauſe hee crowneth
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19944:54"/> his owne gifts, not thy merits. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 120. Againe, <hi>Lord, thou wilt quicken me, in thy Iuſtice, not in mine;</hi> not becauſe I haue deſerued it, but becauſe thou haſt had compaſſion, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 142. See more in the title of <hi>Iuſtification.</hi> Thus I ceaſe to follow them in their idle diſcourſes: concluding our Doctrine to be more auncient, as from Chriſt, the Apoſtles, Scriptures, and Fathers.</p>
                  <p>They obiect places of Scripture for reward. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Reward is two-fold, either of merit, or of mercy. Life euerlaſting is not of merit, but of mercy. Secondly, they obiect merits by couenant, Doe this, and thou ſhalt liue. <hi>Solut.</hi> No man can doe this: <hi>Ergo:</hi> a legall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant condemneth all men. Againe, there is an Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall couenant, this promiſe is made, not to the work, but to the perſon, to his faith, laying hold on Chriſt, <hi>Beleeue, and thou ſhalt be ſaued, Marke 16. 16. Acts</hi> 8. 37. and 16. 31.</p>
                  <p>Now to conclude this poynt for Doctrine, as before of the liues of the Popes. I will vſe the Argument our Sauiour Chriſt vſed againſt the Scribes and Phariſies, who ſaying they had <hi>Abraham</hi> to their father, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. 39. anſwered; <hi>If yee were the children of</hi> Abraham, <hi>ye would doe the deedes of</hi> Abraham: So ſay I, if the Popes be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ſucceſſors, concerning Doctrine, they would ſhew it, in teaching Doctrine agreeable to Scriptures, &amp;c. But this they doe not. For <hi>Peter</hi> taught Iuſtification by faith in Chriſt alone, as the reſt of the Apoſtles; and Chriſt himſelfe, and haue left the ſame written in Scriptures, for our inſtruction and imitation. See title of <hi>Iustification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, <hi>Peter,</hi> Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, teach only two Sacraments of the new teſtament:
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19944:55"/> But they teach ſeauen; contrary to Chriſt, <hi>Peter,</hi> and the Apoſtles. See title of <hi>Sacraments</hi> the number. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, Chriſt inſtituted Baptiſme: the outward ſigne whereof is onely Water; and the forme to baptize, <hi>In the name of the Father, the Sonne, and the Holy Ghoſt. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> the Apoſtles, and Euangeliſts reſted in this: and left the ſame written in Scripture: but the Pope and Papiſts, vſe a number of idle ceremonies, contrary to <hi>Peters</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, the Apoſtles, and Scriptures. See title of <hi>Baptiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, for the Sacrament of the Lords Supper: In the Supper, Chriſt vſed in the Inſtitution thereof bread and wine, as outward ſignes of his body, and his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloud, ſhed in remembrance: but theſe will vſe but one outward ſigne, bread alone. Againe, they will haue Chriſt bodily preſent in the Sacrament, and will vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aboliſh the ſignes, by Tranſubſtantiation, a toy of their owne deuiſing, ſo as no bread ſhall remayne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to common ſence, againſt Chriſt, <hi>Peter,</hi> and Strip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. See <hi>Reall preſence, Supper,</hi> and <hi>Tranſubſtantiation;</hi> and ſo they vtterly deſtroy the Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>Againe, wee teach, no Images to be vſed in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, either publique or priuate, according to the ſecond Commaundement, Scripture, and Churches practiſe, foure hundred yeeres after Chriſt, and euer contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſince: but they iuſtifie Image-ſeruice, as Lay-mens bookes, and the ſeruice of God, directly contrary to Scriptures. See title of <hi>Images.</hi> We teach, that God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is to be worſhipped; neither Saints, nor Angells, and that God is robbed of his honor, by how much is giuen vnto them, &amp;c. according to <hi>Peter,</hi> the Apoſtles, and Scripture. They directly teach the contrary, as deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the office of Chriſt. See title of <hi>Worſhip of Saints.</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:19944:55"/> We teach according to Scripture: No Purgatorie, nor Purgation for ſinne, but the bloud of Chriſt in this life, according to <hi>Peter,</hi> the Apoſtles, &amp; Scriptures. But they teach a Purgatory, to purge ſinnes after death. See title of <hi>Purgatory.</hi> We teach, that neither perſon nor worke, can merit, but the immaculate perſon of Chriſt, God &amp; Man; and his innocent workes, without ſinne. They contrary teach: Merit of perſon, and workes, amongſt ſinfull men. See title of <hi>Merits.</hi> To omit many other Popiſh points of erronious doctrine, we conclude as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: That the Pope is no way <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſour; but an Hereticke, and plaine Antichriſt, fore-told by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, 2 <hi>Theſſal. 2. 4. Which ſitteth as God in the Temple of God, boaſting himſelfe, that he is God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Arguments to proue the Pope Anti-chriſt.</head>
               <p>And firſt, their ſilly reaſons to the contrary.</p>
               <p>The late Counſell of <hi>Lateran</hi> 1517. commanded all Preachers, they ſhould not meddle, nor dare once to ſpeake of the comming of Anti-chriſt: which argueth a guiltie Conſcience.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Now obſerue their Arguments to proue the Pope, not to be Anti chriſt.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Argument: Anti chriſt is but one man, but the Popes haue beene many: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Antichriſt ſhall reigne but 3. yeeres, and a halfe: but the Popes haue reigned many hundreds of yeeres: <hi>Ergo,</hi> not Anti-chriſt.</item>
                     <item>3. Antichriſt ſhall be knowne by name, but the Pope
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19944:56"/> hath ſundry names: <hi>Ergo,</hi> not Anti-chriſt.</item>
                     <item>4. He muſt come of the ſtocke of the Iewes; but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was any Iew Pope: <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. His Seate muſt be at <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> but the Popes Seate is at <hi>Rome: Ergo,</hi> not Anti-chriſt.</item>
                     <item>6. He ſhall manifeſtly deny Chriſt, ſo doth not the Pope (ſay they:) <hi>Ergo, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7. He ſhal doe ſtrange miracles, bring fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, cauſe Images to ſpeake: ſo doth not: <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8. He ſhall wage great battell, and conqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> all the world: theſe agree not with the Pope: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Pope is not Anti-chriſt. See the anſwer of theſe in <hi>D. Willet Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſis. fol.</hi> 273. in quarto.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>Now, to proue the Pope to be Anti-chriſt, we neede looke for no further proofe, then the Scripture: he being ſo liuely deſcribed there, which we truſt ſhall appeare euident to all men. Note well the places.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>DAn.</hi> 11. which contains a Prophecie of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms which ſhould be enimies vnto the Church of God; verſe 3. of <hi>Greece;</hi> verſe 5. of <hi>Aegipt;</hi> verſe 28. of <hi>Syria;</hi> verſe 36. of the <hi>Romans,</hi> vnder <hi>Antiochus, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes,</hi> by whom the Pope is figured, it is ſaid; <hi>He ſhall doe what he will.</hi> This is moſt true of the Pope, his will muſt ſtand for reaſon. <hi>Diſtinct. 96. cap. Satis. If the Pope ſhall draw infinit ſoules to hell,</hi> no man is to ſay vnto him; <hi>Sir, why doe you ſo?</hi> In like manner, where he tooke the Cuppe from the Laitie, in receiuing the Lords Supper; it is hereſie to ſpeak againſt it, <hi>non obſtante,</hi> that is, though Chriſt did inſtitute it ſo: Againe, the Pope may not be
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19944:56"/> iudged, for he is called, Our Lord God the Pope Look <hi>Decrees</hi> 96. They ſay, God, and the Pope haue all one Conſiſtorie: therefore the Pope may doe what he will, verſe 37. It is ſaid, <hi>He ſhall not care for the God of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:</hi> No more doth the Pope; for he hath inuented, and erected a new breaden god, which his fathers neuer knew. Nor, <hi>for the deſires of women,</hi> for he hath prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited lawfull marriage; and permitteth adultery, and Sodometry. Nor, <hi>care for any God, for hee ſhall mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie himſelfe aboue all:</hi> So doth the Pope: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Argument: 2 <hi>Theſſal. 2. 4. Paules</hi> deſcription in euery point is verified in the Pope: <hi>He ſhall exalt himſelfe aboue God: and euery thing, &amp;c.</hi> So the Pope hath chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged the full authority of Chriſt (as before) and exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe aboue Emperours, and Kings, which are called Gods vpon earth: yea, the Pope hath calculated the difference betweene him and them, ſaying, the Pope is 47. degrees aboue the Emperour; as the Sunne is 47. degrees bigger then the Moone. <hi>Innocent</hi> the third in his <hi>Decretals.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>He ſhal ſit in the Temple,</hi> that is, in the Church, and hath the Keyes (as he boaſteth) of heauen, and hell, verſe 9. <hi>Anti-chriſt ſhall come with lying ſignes.</hi> So doth the Pope, &amp;c. verſe 11. <hi>God ſhall ſend ſtrong illuſions:</hi> Neuer ſo ſtrong as in Popery; as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſecuteth the ſonne: <hi>&amp; è contra:</hi> Huſbands their Wiues, Maſters their Seruants; <hi>&amp; è contra;</hi> verſe 3. Anti-chriſt is called the man of Sinne, and a wicked man. Where ſhall wee finde more wickedneſſe then in the Popes? Some Coniurers, <hi>Silueſter</hi> the ſecond; ſome in league with the Diuell, <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt; whoore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19944:57"/> inceſtuous, Sodomites, blaſphemers: <hi>Ergo,</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-chriſts. See before, <hi>the Concluſion of the Popes liues. fol.</hi> 78.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Argument: <hi>Reuel. 8. 10. He is a Starre fallen from Heauen.</hi> So the Pope is departed from the ancient faith of <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſuperſtition, and idolatry, he hath the keyes of the bottomleſſe pit. Who but the Pope giueth the Croſſe-keyes? who (ſaith he) may carry downe to hell with him Chariots loaden with ſoules? <hi>cap. Si Papa. Distinct. 42. verſ. 3. Locuſts ariſing out of the bottomleſſe pit:</hi> that is, innumerable ſwarmes of begging Friers, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Argument: <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17. 5. The ſeate of Antichriſt is deſcribed, in her fore-head a name written, <hi>a Mystery, Great Babylon,</hi> that is, <hi>Rome,</hi> the Commaunder (at that time) of all the world. And after the Emperours decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the Pope, which commaundeth Emperours and Kings, verſe 3. The <hi>ſeauen heads</hi> are ſeauen mountains, ſo is <hi>Rome</hi> built vpon ſeauen mountaines, &amp;c. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Pope Antichriſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Argument: 1 <hi>Iohn 2. 22. Who is a lier, the ſame is Antichriſt, that denyeth the Father and the Sonne.</hi> Who but the Pope that exalteth himſelfe againſt <hi>all that is called God:</hi> diſpenſing againſt the law of Nature: againſt the precepts of the old and new Teſtament. <hi>Vide Willet. fol.</hi> 282.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Argument: 2 <hi>Theſſ. 2. 24. An Aduerſary, &amp;c.</hi> The Pope is an aduerſary in doctrine, liuing and teaching cleane contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and liuing cleane contrary to Chriſt, and his Apoſtles. See before, <hi>for life,</hi> and <hi>doctrine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:19944:57"/>
                  <p n="7">7. Argument: <hi>Reuelat. 17. 1. Anti-chriſt is called the Great Whoore.</hi> So, <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 853. There was a right whoore elected Pope, called <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight; but it fell out to be <hi>Ioane,</hi> bigge with childe. See the Storie before. fol. 16. She ſate two yeeres and ſixe moneths; though ſome left her out of the Catalogue for ſhame, as <hi>Marian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Scotus</hi> writeth.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Argument: <hi>Reuel.</hi> 13. 11. This place plainely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth Anti-chriſt: which ſucceeded the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, as vile, verſe 12. and as powerfull.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>See the Fathers.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BErnard</hi> ſaith, The beaſt in the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> vnto whom is giuen a mouth, to ſpeake blaſphemies, occupieth <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 125.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ioachim Abbas</hi> ſaith, Anti-chriſt was lately borne at <hi>Rome:</hi> vpon the <hi>Reuel. lib. 10. part.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>The Biſhops in the Counſell of <hi>Rainſpurge</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>Hildebrand</hi> the Pope, vnder the colour of Religion, laid the foundation of Anti-chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregory</hi> the firſt, and the beſt of all the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> that followed, ſaith: I doe confidently affirme, that whoſoeuer doth call himſelfe Vniuerſall Biſhop, or deſire ſo to be called, is the fore-runner of Anti-chriſt in his pride. <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 591.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bernard</hi> vpon the words of Chriſt, <hi>Matth. 10. 42. The Lords of the Nations reigne, &amp;c. but it ſhall not be ſo among you:</hi> ſaith to Pope <hi>Eugenius;</hi> It is plaine that here domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is forbidden the Apoſtles. Go to then, dare, &amp; ye will, to take vpon you ruling an Apoſtleſhip: or in your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtleſhip rule, or dominion. If you will haue both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19944:58"/> you ſhall looſe both: Otherwiſe you muſt not thinke your ſelfe exempt from the number of them, of whom the Lord complayneth thus. <hi>They haue reigned, but not of me; they haue beene, but I haue not knowne them. De conſideratione ad Eugenium. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon 2 <hi>Theſſ. 3. 4. 6. Hom.</hi> 4. As long as the Empire ſhall be had in awe, no man ſhall ſtraightly ſubmit himſelfe to Anti-chriſt: but after the Empire ſhall be diſſolued, Anti-chriſt ſhall inuade the ſtate of the Empire: it ſtanding voyde, hee ſhall labour to pull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe the Empire both of man, and God. Who ſeeth not at this day the Empire diſſolued, and the Pope euen Anti-chriſt to dominiere ouer Emperors &amp; Kings?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hilarie ad Auxentium. Hierome ad Algaſiam, queſtion.</hi> 11. and <hi>Oecumenius</hi> vpon 2 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 2. will not admit that Anti-chriſt ſhould ſit at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but in the Church of God.</p>
                  <p>For the moſt part, all Princes and Biſhops in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and <hi>Italie,</hi> haue publiſhed and called <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeauenth, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the two and twentieth Anti-chriſt. <hi>Auentinus. Anal. lib. 5. &amp;</hi> 7.</p>
                  <p>See the ſentence of Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth, fol. 17. againſt the Popes. See <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeauenth, fol. 27. where the Popes call one another Anti-chriſt. Let them be iudged from their owne mouthes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>Thus hauing (through Gods mercy) brought this buſineſſe to an end, further then I euer intended it. And ſeeing it pleaſed not God to giue it that effect, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto I laboured, in the particular, yet it may pleaſe him ſo to bleſſe and proſper it, as it ſhall not returne in
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19944:58"/> vaine vnto him; which hath ſeene my deſire, my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and ſtudie (in mine olde age) for them that are not yet called. Vnto whom I moſt humbly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Labour, and them to be bleſſed of him. Exhorting all the true Succeſſours of <hi>Peter,</hi> I meane the Paſtours of Congregations: to haue a care of their liues and Doctrine, that ſo labouring together faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, to gather into one, the Sheepe that are ſcattered abroad, into the folde of IESVS CHRIST, when the great Shep-heard ſhall appeare, wee may giue vp an account with ioy, and not with griefe, ſaying; <hi>Theſe are thoſe</hi> (LORD) <hi>which thou haſt giuen me.</hi> To whom be aſcribed of vs, all glory, praiſe, power, and thankeſ-giuing, for euer and euer:</p>
               <closer>Amen.</closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
